好的，我们开始吧。
Okay, let's get started.
是的。所以我希望你喜欢APA二，对吧？
Yeah. So I hope you enjoy APA two, right?
你昨天拿到了第二题的参考答案，对吧？
You got a reference answer for second question yesterday, right?
你今天也从Deepsk那里拿到了第一题的参考答案，对吧？
And you get a reference answer to question one today from Deepsk, right?
希望你喜欢。如果你不知道怎么优化，其实可以检查一下你的代码。
I hope you enjoy. And if you have no idea how to optimize, you can actually check your code.
嗯，好。今天我们要完成并行性这一部分。
Yeah. Okay. And today, we are going to finish parallelism.
今天我们有很多深入的内容。
We have a lot of deep contents today.
所以下一节课开始，我们会更深入地学习Ms。
So starting from the next lecture, we are going to dive deeper into Ms.
我们会用到上一节课学到的内容，
We are going to use what we learned in the previous lecture,
然后把它们应用到Ms上。我们今天尽量完成。
and we apply them into Ms. Let's try to finish today.
简单回顾一下，对吧？嗯，基本上，在我上一节课中，
Just to recap, right? Um, so basically, in my last lecture,
我们建立了一个模型，帮助你分析Interop或流水线部分的开销
we developed a model that help you analyze the overhead from Interop or pipeline parts
流水线部分的开销，对吧？
the overhead of Pipeline partism, right?
这是甘特图。我认为这个模型的核心是
This is the ganchart. And I think the core of this model is
基本上你关心的是“气泡”，对吧？
basically you care about the bubble, right?
你想要最小化这个“气泡”，明白吗？
You want to minimize the bubble, okay?
然后我们开发了第一个调度方案，也就是GPip调度，
And we develop our first schedule, which is the GPip schedule,
这是一个非常结构化且看起来很漂亮的调度方案，但它并不起作用。
which is a very structured and nice looking schedule, but it doesn't work.
为什么？因为内存与lumber microbde大小一致。
Why? Because the memory is green with lumbar microbde size.
好吗？然后我们修复了它，对吧？
Okay? And we fix it, right?
我们把时间表弄得有点乱，但它是可行的，好吗？
We make the schedule a little bit messier, but it works, okay?
然后我们尝试让它不断推进。
And we try to advance it further and further.
我们开始开发另一种模式的时间表，就是双向的。
We start developing another mode schedule, which is bidirectional.
我们说这是用来深度训练的，好吗？
And we said that this is one used to train deep, okay?
这个叫做奇美拉（Chimera）。
This one called Chimera.
好的，我想我们就停在这里。
Okay, and I think we stopped here.
好的，那我们继续吧。
Okay. Then let's continue.
所以对于我在上一节课介绍的所有时间表，
So for all the schedules I introduced in my last lecture,
我给它们起了一个名字，就是它们被称为同步流水线并行时间表。
I give them a name that is, um, they are called synchronous Pipeline parallel schedule.
在这里，你可以理解同步其实非常相似。
So here, you can understand that synchronous are something very similar
就像我们在数据并行中讨论的那样，我们总是确保
to what we discussed in data parism that is we always make
所有的工作节点都在同一个地方。
sure like all the workers, they are in the same place.
那我是什么意思呢？这种方法的主要好处是
So what do I mean? So the main benefits of this kind of like method is that it
它保留了机器学习的语义。
keeps machine learning semantics.
换句话说，整个训练过程将完全一样。
So in other words, the whole training competition will be exactly the same.
就好像你实际上只在单个设备上运行一样，因为如果你看预先的调度，
Uh, as if you're actually new on single device because if you look at the pre schedule,
我们总是有这个同步屏障。
we always have this barrier.
我们会在所有微批次完成后再进行更新。
We update when all the micro baatches are finished.
但其实，这里有一点空间可以让我们操作，从而让这个过程
Okay. But actually, there's a little space that we can play around that to make this a little bit
更加同步，同时速度更快。
more synchronous but much faster.
就像我说的，在这种同步调度下，主要的缺点是会有气泡，
So um, like I said, in this kind of synchronous schedule, the main downside is we have bubbles,
尽管随着你增加lumbar microbachs气泡会减少，但我们还是会有气泡，
and although the bubble will diminish as you increase lumbar microbachs but we have bubbles, um,
我们已经讨论了很多减少气泡的算法，但是，
and we have discussed many algorithms to reduce the bubble, but,
要减少这种流水线气泡，基本上需要你大幅增加lamb microbatches。
reducing this pipeline bubble requires you basically very radically increase lamb microbatches.
比如说，如果你的输入较小，没有足够的空间来做很多，
So for example, if you have a smaller input, which you don't have a lot of space to make many,
很多microbtches，在这种情况下，你的流水线并行性就不会特别高效。
many microbtches in that case, your pipeline parism is not going to be super efficient.
好的，现在我们来看另一种研究方向。
Okay. Now, let's look at another line of work.
另一种流水线并行调度类型，或者说
So another type of pipeline parallel schedule or what
我们称之为同步流水线并行调度，在这种方式下我们基本上移除了
we call the synchronous pipeline parallel schedule, where we basically remove
流水线调度中的同步点，现在我们可以开始下一轮了
the synchronization point in the pipeline schedule, um, and now we can start the next round
在上一轮的反向传播还没完成时，就开始了前向传播。
forward forward pass before the backward pass of the previous round finished.
好的，也就是说我们移除了一个屏障更新。
Okay. That is we remove a barrier update.
好的，而同步调度实际上没有流水线气泡，但它也打破了
Okay. And a synchronous schedule actually don't have pipeline bubbles, but it also breaks
就像我说的，同步语义。
like I said, the synchronous semantics.
也就是说，如果你用这种流水线调度，你用这个
That is, if you use this kind of pipeline schedule, your model trained with this
流水线调度训练出来的模型，其实和你在单个设备上训练是不一样的，对吧？
pipeline schedule is different from, uh, as if you are training on a single device. Okay?
因为你的梯度在某种程度上变得滞后了。
Because your grading becomes steel in some way.
就像我们在数据并行中做的那样。
Okay, like what we did in, um, data parism.
好的，我们来看，第一个基本上就是这个。
Okay, let's see. The first one is basically this one.
如果我们希望所有设备都能自由地、以自己的节奏排队执行，
If we like all the devices to go free and acute at their own pace,
我们基本上得到了这个我称之为AMP net的调度方式。
we basically get this schedule which I called AMP net.
每个设备只要空闲时就会执行前向传播。
And each device basically performs forward pass whenever free.
它们在每次反向传播后都会更新权重。
And they update the wise after every Brod pass.
好的。采用这种调度方式，前向和反向传播的不同阶段
Okay. And with this schedule, the different stages in the forward and Bro pass
可以在不同版本的权重上进行，对吧？
can be on different versions of the WIC, right?
因为每个设备都是按照自己的节奏进行更新的。
Because each device update on their own pace.
举个例子，比如对于数据0.1，对于数据1，第一阶段和第二阶段的前向传播，
Okay? For example, here for the Data 0.1, for the data one, the forward pass of stage one and two,
用的是初始权重，而前向传播和反向传播
on the initial width, where the forward pass on who backward pass
以及反向传播用的是数据0更新后的权重。
and backward pass on weights updated by data zero.
这样权重的不一致会给训练过程带来噪声，对吗？
Okay? So this discrepancy brings noise to the training process, right?
因为在原始的SED中，我们会确保先更新，然后做梯度下降，再更新。
Because in original SED, we make sure we update and then dp gradient and then update.
但在这里，每个设备基本上都按照不同的节奏进行。
But here, every device basically follow a different pace.
这也是为什么这种方法其实效果不是很好，明白吗？
And that's why this one actually doesn't work pretty well, okay?
在像mist或者Cipher这种小型的图像分类模型上还可以用。
On smart that's like a mist or Cipher this kind of small um, image classifier models.
它可以工作，但在更大的语言模型上就很可能不行。
It works, but very likely that amor language models.
这会导致发散。
This will lead to divergence.
好的，还有一些工作是为了提升这个MP net算法的收敛性。
Okay? Um, and there are also some work that, improve the convergence of this MP net, um, algorithm.
其中一个叫做pipe Myer，它通过修改梯度优化器来提升收敛性，
One is called pipe Myer and it modifies the grading optimizer to improve the convergence,
但是提升其实非常有限。
um, but just a little bit improve.
它并不能从根本上改变这个问题，明白了吗？
It cannot fundamentally change the drawbo this way, okay?
嗯，Pipe Dream 是另一种通过减少同步来实现更好收敛的算法。
Um, and pipe dream is another, algorithm that achieves better convergence
它通过减少这种同步来实现。
by reducing this synchrony.
所以，Pipe Dream 算法的时间线看起来和 1f1b 非常相似，对吧。
So, the timeline of the pipe dream algorithm looks very similar to 1f1b, right.
它看起来和 1f1b 非常相似。
It looks very similar to 1f1b.
但是，嗯，主要的区别在于，我们是在反向传播完成后才更新模型。
But, um, the main difference here is, um, we updated the model was once the backward has finished.
好的，这里的主要思想基本上是我们尝试在
Okay. The main idea here is basically we try to enforce in the same version of
前向和反向传播时对单个输入数据点使用相同版本的权重。
weight for the forward and backward pass of a single input data point.
这其实是放宽了约束条件。
It's basically relaxed constraint.
让我们专注于设备一，好吗？这就是设备一。
And let's focus on device one, okay? So this is device one.
对于输入批次 0 到 3 的前向和反向传播，我们使用
And for the forward and backward pass of the input batches, zero to three, we use
相同的初始权重。你可以看到。
the same initial weight. You can see.
好吗？嗯，但是对于输入批次四来说。
Okay? Um, but for input batch four.
它使用的是由输入批次零更新后的权重。
Um, it uses the width updated by input battery zero.
因为我们在对输入一到三进行反向传播时，仍然需要使用初始权重，
Since we still need to use the initial weights for the backward pass of input one to three,
在这个时间点，我们会有两份权重的副本。
and at this time point, we will have two copies of weights.
一份是初始权重，另一份是基本上在我们对输入零计算后更新的权重，对吧？
One initial weight and one width, that is, basically updated after we compute on input zero, right?
嗯，然后对于输入批次五，我们需要更新权重，嗯，
Um, and again, for input B five, we need to update weights, um,
我们需要使用由输入零和一更新后的权重。
we need to use width updated by the input zero and one.
好吗？对于输入六，我们需要使用由数据批次零、一和二更新后的权重。
Okay? And for input six, we need to use width updated by data bat zero, one and two.
因此，总的来说，嗯，我们需要存储四份权重的副本。
Therefore, in total, um, we need to store four copies of it.
好吗？但我们只把神经网络分成了四个阶段。
Okay? But we only divide the neural network into four stages.
这个美好幻想最大的缺点就是根本无法节省内存。
The biggest downside of this pipe dream is that there will be no memory saving at all.
对吧？记住，当我们做流水线棱镜时，我们把神经网络分成了四个阶段。
Right? Remember, when we do pipeline prism, we divide the neural network into four stages.
这就是我们消耗内存的原因。
That's why we consume memory.
但这个算法基本上违背了我们的初衷。
But this algorithm basically defeat our purpose.
你需要在每个设备上存储四份副本。
You need to store four copies on each device.
好吗？但这只是一个非常初步的、类似论文讨论的内容
Okay? But this was just a very initial, kind of like paper discussing
讨论了异步流水线桶调度，并讨论了这种可能性。
a synchronous pipeline barrel schedule and discussing that possibility.
这就是我提起这个的原因，好吗。
That's why I bring this up, okay.
而且现在，我觉得大家一直在跟进。
And today, I think people have been following up
有很多新的方法可以比这个做得更好。
a lot of new work which can do better than this one.
是的，好的。为了减少内存使用，PipeDream 的作者们，
Yeah. Okay. And to reduce the memory usage, um, the pipe dream authors,
他们对原始的流水线算法提出了一个修改，
they propose a modification to the original pipeline,
通过不那么频繁地更新宽度，这被称为 PipeDream 2 PW。
papeream algorithm by updating the width less frequently, um, which is called pipe dream two PW.
比如这里，输入补丁4、5、6仍然使用初始宽度。
For example, here, input patch, four, five, six, still use the initial width.
从输入7开始，我们会使用由输入0到3更新后的宽度。
And starting uh, input seven, we will use the width updated by inputs zero to three.
因此，梯度总是只为一次更新而存储。
Therefore, the greens are always only stored for one update, y.
这样你就可以减少存储需求。
And you can reduce the story.
好的，这位 PipeDream 的作者，他是个非常有名的人。
Okay. And this Pablo Author, he's a very famous guy.
他基本上是流水线并行的先驱，后来加入了NVIDIA，整个Megatron项目也是他参与的。
He basically was a pioneer in doing Pipeline Pism and he joined Adia, and the entire Megatron
这个库主要是他写的。
library was written mostly by him.
好吗？Megatron 基本上是大家用来
Okay? Megatron is basically the framework that people use
在社区中训练语言模型的一个框架。是的，没错。
a lot in community to train language models. Yeah. Okay.
这项工作相当不错，对吧？
This is pretty good work, okay?
呃，可能还会有其他不同的流水线
Uh, there might be different there will be more different pipeline
调度方式我们还没有涉及，但有一个重要的问题我们还没讨论，
schedules that we haven't covered, but one important issue, we haven't discussed is basically
就是对于我们刚才展示的所有流水线调度算法，
for all the pipeline scheduling algorithm, um, we showed just now, right,
我们假设不同流水线阶段的运行时间
we assume the running times of different pipeline stages are
和上面这个图中完全一样，对吧？
exactly the same as in this figure above, right?
所以基本上 ABCD 这几个阶段的长度是一样的，对吗？
So basically ABCD they are of the same lens, right?
Um, But if the latency of these stages are not the same, for example, the timeline will be
looking like this, right?
So basically for a single input, for each different input, you will have
different kind of like executing time.
And you can see this is much worse, right?
In the upper figure, when we execute four batches, we are there.
But here, basically the time becomes longer.
Okay? So one important factor when you do pipeline parison,
you need to make sure each device has the same workload.
Does that make sense?
好的。我们稍后再讨论这个，好吗？
Okay. We'll discuss this later, okay?
好的。现在有很多人在研究如何将 New 分成不同的阶段，
Okay. There are many studying how to partition on New into different stages,
主要目标基本上是尽量减少最大阶段延迟，
and the main goal is basically trying to minimize the maximum stage latency
以提升流水线效率，也就是整体流水线效率。嗯，
to improve pipeline efficiency, the overall pipeline efficiency. Um,
同时还要尽量优化不同分支在设备上的分布。
And also try to maximize the pization of different branches in device placement.
这里我给大家介绍一下这两类方法的概况。
And here I give you an overview of these two class methods.
我不会全部讲完，但如果你想深入了解，
I'm not going to cover all of them, but if you want to dive deeper,
可以阅读这些论文。基本上分为两大类。
read these papers. Essentially two categories.
第一类其实是你们非常熟悉的套路，
The first category is basically the same recipe you are very familiar
因为我们在 Matamo 的编译器或者像图处理时也用过这个方法。
with because we did this for compilers for, um Matamo for like a graph
这是关于系统的机器学习。
open that is machine learning for systems.
我们尝试学习一个能够给我们最佳调度的模型。
We try to learn a model that can give us the best schedule.
这个模型通常是通过逆向学习训练出来的。好的，这是左边的部分。
And this model was usually trained using inverse learning. Okay, the left part.
第二部分是我们明确地将这个流水线调度建模为一个优化问题，
The second part is we explicitly model this pipeline schedule as an oppimentation,
然后我们尝试去解决这个优化问题。
and we try to solve that openation.
但有时候这个优化问题可能是不可追踪的，
But sometimes this opmentation is probably in trackable,
所以会花很长时间，因为它有点难，嗯，你知道的，就是这样。
so it takes forever, because it is a bit hard and, um, so, you know, yeah.
好的，我会简单介绍一下第一个调度的基本思路。
Okay, I will basically give you a brief idea of the first scheduling.
这是一个致力于优化流水线调度的工作。
And this is a work that basically trying to optimize the pipeline for schedule.
基本上，这项工作叫做Plato。
So basically, this work is called Plato.
所以基本上，RO 的例子就是分区算法，而 I 算法的环境如图所示，
So basically, is the example of RO is partition algorithm, and the environment for
其中状态是计算图的一个具体设备放置方案。
the I algorithm is defined as in this figure where the state is a specific
动作是修改图中某个节点的设备分配。
device placement plan for computing graph.
奖励基本上是新旧放置方案之间的延迟差异。
Um, the action is to modify the device assignment of a node in the graph.
R 智能体是一个图神经网络，它试图作为一个
And the reward is basically a latency difference between the new and the old placement.
策略，找出如何将这些节点放置在不同设备上的最佳方式，
And the R agent is a graph neural network that's trying to, um, try to basically perform as
以最大化奖励，也就是最小化延迟，对吧？
a policy and try to figure out what is the right way to place these notes on
人们基本上就是这样做的，这其实就像是在搜索。
different devices in order to maximize the reward, which is equivalent to minimizing latency, okay?
你不断尝试不同的放置策略，
And people basically, do this, and, it's basically like a search.
然后把它部署到集群上，观察延迟，
You keep trying different placement strategy and, you put it on a cluster observe latency,
然后你把奖励反向传播到新网络，大概就是这样，明白了吗？酷。
and then you propagate the reward back to new network, something like that, okay? Cool.
有什么问题吗？有。这是稀疏线稀疏。
Any questions? Yeah. This is the spars Wire sparse.
怎么做到的？他们只是用更多的计算机来训练模型。
How? They just use more computer to train a model.
对，继续尝试。
Yeah. Keep trying.
好的，好的，嗯，总结一下，互操作并行的思想是分配
Okay. Okay, um I summary, the idea of interop parism is to assign
计算图的不同操作符到不同的设备上，然后
different operators of the computation graph to different devices and then
以流水线并行的方式执行，对吧？
execute in pipeline parallel fashion, right?
设备分配算法基本上是并行化不同的图分支，
The device placement algorithm basically paralyze different graph branches,
但他们有个问题，就是并不是所有的图都适用。
but they have a problem they are not applicable on all graphs.
这是这里的第一类。
That's the first category here.
嗯，第二类，同步流水线调度其实是我们经常用的，好吗？
Um, the second category, synchronized pipeline schedule is the one that
实际上我们用得很多，好吗？
actually we used a lot, okay?
它的收敛性和你在单设备上是一样的，
And it has the same convergence as if you are on single device,
并且有很多算法可以减少流水线气泡并提升硬件利用率。
and there are many algorithms on reducing the pipeline bubbles and improving hardware condition.
嗯，第三类，我刚刚讲过，基本上是
Um, and the third category, which I just covered is basically
异步流水线Barrel调度。
a synchronous pipeline Barrel schedule.
它的硬件利用率最高，因为你可以
It has the highest hardware utilization because you can
基本上减少，基本上可以做到零气泡，
basically reduce you can basically have zero bubble,
对，因为你可以随意调度你想要的任务。
right, because you just schedule whatever you want.
是的，你不用关心收敛性。
Yeah, you don't care about convergence.
它没有管道气泡，但引入了三星同步机制，
And it has no pipe bubble, but it introduce samsung synchrony,
我们在机器融合中听说过这个。
which we heard in machinering convergence.
所以它只适用于某些问题，并不是所有问题都适用。
So it is only applicable on some problems, but not all problems.
明白了吗？这些调度方式在阶段均衡时表现最好，
Okay? So all these schedules perform the best when you have a balanced stage,
也就是说每个阶段需要有大致相同的工作负载。
that is each stage need to have roughly the same workload.
否则，你会看到那张图，对吧？
Otherwise, you observe that graph, right?
好的，酷。这基本上标志着流水线并行调度的结束。
Okay. Cool. This basically marks the end of, uh, pipeline par schedule.
我认为直到今天，人们还在这个领域发表论文。
I think up until today, people are still publishing this area.
他们写了越来越多的论文，试图提出更好的调度方法。是的，请问。
They are writing more and more papers to coming up with a better schedule. Yeah, please.
有办法让它们同步在一起吗？
Is there a way synchronous together?
不，你不能这样做，因为一旦你的模型参数变成同步的，
No, you cannot because once your model parameter becomes a synchronous,
梯度更新就是顺序进行的，你更新，你更新，你更新，你更新。
grading is sequential, you update, you update, you update, you update.
一旦在早期步骤你进行了更新，并且你用的是静态梯度，那么你的轨迹就会
Once at the early step, you update and you are using a steel gradit, then your trajectory is
和使用同步方式的轨迹不同。
different from using a synchronous one.
你不能回头。明白吗？
You cannot go back. Yeah. Does that make sense?
嗯，好的，明白了。那我们继续吧，好吗？
Yeah, okay. Okay. Then let's move on, okay.
让我们进入更有趣的部分，比如模型，或者我们如何建模内部并行，对吧？
Let's move into a more interesting, like a model or how we model the intraop partism, right?
我觉得关于跨并行我们已经讨论过了。
I think for interpartism, we already talk about that.
基本上就是气泡。明白吗？
It's basically the bubble. Okay.
每当你谈到流水线并行中的中断时，你就要想到气泡，明白吗？
Whenever you talk about pipeline PismT about interrupt, you think bubble, okay?
但在内部并行中，这个问题会更复杂一些。
But in intra, this is more kind of, like, complicated.
好吗？我们该如何建模呢？
Okay? How we model this?
基本上，内部并行简单回顾一下，就是我们会把一个算子进行划分，
So basically intra Pism just to recap, right, we will partition a single operator and
并且探索该算子内部的并行性，对吧？
explore the parism inside of that operator, right?
所以下面的幻灯片中，我们将学习如何对一个算子进行并行化。
And so basically in the following slides, we are going to study how to paralyze a single operator.
一旦我们知道如何对一个算子并行化，我们就可以推广到
And once we know how to paralyze a single operator, we can generalize it to
基本上如何对整个算法中的所有算子进行并行化。
basically how to paralyze all the operators in algram.
我们还会建立一个数学模型，帮助你分析代价，好吗？
And we are going to develop a model mathematical model to help you analyse the cost, okay?
那我们继续吧。
So let's move on.
我们还是从最简单的情况开始。
So let's still begin with the simplest case.
我想这个问题我已经在很多不同的讲座中讲过很多次了。
I think this one I have covered this many, many times in different lectures.
所以这是逐元素操作，对吧？
So this is animal wise operator, right?
这里有一个对二维张量进行逐元素加法的代码。
And here's a code for an animal wise addition on two dimensional tensors.
好吗？这段代码对应着一个两层的for循环，如这里所示。
Okay? And the code corresponds to two level four loop, which is there.
好的，通过观察这两层for循环，
Okay, by observing this two level four loop,
你会发现这两个for循环之间没有依赖关系。
you observe that there's no dependency on these 24 loops.
好的，所以基本上，没有依赖关系。
Okay. So basically, no dependency.
这个for循环就是完全独立的。你可以交换它们的顺序。
This follop just go independent. You can swap the order.
好的，没关系。
Okay, doesn't matter.
我强调这一点的原因是，因为没有依赖关系，
Okay. The reason I highlight this is because um because there's no dependency,
所以我们可以把这四个循环任意分配到不同的设备上实现并行，对吧？
so we can arbitrarily split the four loops on different devices for paralyzation, right?
现在，如果我们有四个设备，用四种不同的颜色表示，那么有多种方式
Now, if we have four devices denoted by the four different colors, then there are multiple ways
来并行化这个操作，对吧。
to paralyze this operator, right.
比如说，我们可以并行化这个N循环，也就是最外层的循环，对吧？
So for example, we can paralyze this loop N, which is the outer loop, right?
我们也可以并行化D循环，也就是内层循环，对吧？
We can also paralyze the loop D, which is the inner loop, right?
基本上，当我们在这个图中并行N循环时，在这种情况下，所有三个都需要
And uh so basically, when we pariselop N in this figure, and in this case, all three confers how to
进行行分区，对吧？
be row partition, right?
因为你需要给每个设备分配一些任务。
Because you need to give each device some work to do.
如果你选择对N循环进行分区，那么，输入数组A和B，
And if you choose to partition the loop N, then, um, the input array A and B,
它们需要按照行分区的方式，在四个设备上进行分割，对吧？
they need to be partitioned following the low partition, right on four devices,
结果会被写入输出设备的一行分区中。明白了吗？
and the result will be written in a row parting way at the output device. Okay?
很合理，对吧。很好。你会注意到，当你这样做时，没有通信成本。
Makes sense, right. Cool. One thing you observe is when you do this, there's no communication cost.
你只需要进行分区就可以了。这样就没问题了。
You just do your partitioning. You are good.
或者我们也可以像右图所示，同时并行化两个循环和循环D。
Or we can paralyze both loop and loop D, as shown in the right figure.
在这种情况下，所有张量都沿着行和列机器进行分区。
In this case, all tensors are partitioned along both row and column machine.
每个设备基本上存储原始张量的一个子区域，并在自己的分区上工作。
Each device basically stores a sub region of the original tensor and works on its own separation.
在这种情况下，依然没有通信。
In this case, there's still no communication.
是的，因为这两者的区别基本上就是你如何进行分区或者
Yeah, because the difference between these two is basically you partition or you
你如何分配区域。
assign regions differently.
但都没有通信。明白了吗？所以基本上，这取决于维度。
But there's no communication. Okay. So basically, depending on the dimension
关于张量和lumber设备的例子，比如说，我可以把这个推广到
of the tensor and the lumber devices, for example, I can generalize this into
四维张量，或者在transformer中，对吧？
four dimensional tensor or the in transformer, right?
我可以有一千个设备。
I can have 1,000 devices.
好的。并且根据这个张量的维度以及lumber设备的数量，
Okay. And depending on this dimension of tensor and also the lumbre devices,
还有很多其他的变体。
there are a lot of other variants.
比如说，对于五维张量，就会有五层for循环，
And, for example, for five dimensional tensor, there's a five level four loop,
这会导致更多的部分历史记录。
and, which leads to more part histrgs.
但这里的关键是没有依赖关系，所以没有通信。
But the thing here is no dependency, so there's no communication.
明白了吗？当然，我们会这样做，对吧？
Okay? Of course, we're going to do this, right?
那我们继续往下讲更复杂的情况，met M。好的。
So let's move on to more complicated case, met M. Okay.
Met mo 基本上对应于这个三层的 for 循环，对吧？
Met mo basically corresponds to this three level for loop, right?
同样地，我们可以并行化一个循环，也可以把多个循环一起并行化，
And similarly, we can paralyze one loop or we can paralyze several loops together,
并将计算分配到不同的设备上。
and assign the computation to different devices.
好的。那么我们来逐个看看每个循环，好吗？
Okay. So basically, let's look at each loop, okay?
所以循环 I 和循环 J，它们非常容易并行化，因为没有依赖关系，对吧？
So loop I and loop J, they are very easy to paralyze because there's no dependency, right?
它们是独立的循环。
They are the independent loops.
好的，并且在这四个循环中没有依赖，我们可以任意地把
Okay. And no carried on these four loops, and we can arbitrarily split
这两个循环分配到不同的设备上。
these two loops on different devices.
但复杂的是在 Mami 中，基本上我们有一个 K 循环。这个 K 循环，
But the complicates in Mami basically we have a loop K. This loop K,
我们称之为归约循环，因为在这个 K 循环中，我们在累加结果。
we call it a reduction loop because in this loop k, we are accumulating the results.
我觉得你在作业里做过这个。
I think you did this in your homework.
这是一个归约循环，如果我们并行化K循环，基本上需要累加
This is a reduction loop, and if we paralyze loop K, we basically need to accumulate
所有设备的部分结果，这可以通过什么实现？
the partial results from all devices, which can be done by by what?
生物通信原语，那是什么？
Bio coommunication primitive, what is that?
或者用reduce。对，因为我们有部分结果，所以基本上是累加结果。
Or reduce. Yeah. Because we have partial results, so basically accumulate results.
同样，如果我们有四个设备，用四种不同的颜色表示，我们还用灰色
Again, if we have four devices denoted by four different colors, we also use gray
来表示一个张量是否被复制。
here to denote if a tensor is replicated or not.
所以首先，我们可以并行化，呃，基本上是I循环。
So first, we can paralyze, uh, basically loop I.
这意味着矩阵C和A必须被分区。
This means that matrix C and A have to be partitioned.
每个设备，嗯，这里的区别没问题。
Each device, um, so here, this difference okay.
这与之前的 phi Y 是元素加法不同。
This is different from pre phis Y is element addition.
但是在这里，如果我选择对 A 的循环 I 进行分区，那么 A 就会被
But here, if I choose to partition A loop I then A will be
分区，而 B，I 基本上是 A 的一个维度，I 也是结果矩阵的一个维度。
partition Be I is basically a dimension of A, and I is also dimension of the resulting matrix.
但在这里，我不能对 B 进行分区，为什么？
But here, I cannot part in B, why?
因为如果我选择对循环进行分区，那么 B 必须在所有设备上进行复制。
Because if I choose to partition loop, then B has to be replicated across all devices.
不，这里的区别，MO 是非常不同的。
No the difference, MO is quite different.
好的，嗯，好的。
Okay. Um, okay.
为了计算这个分配的部分，每个设备都必须访问
In order to compute this assigned portion, each device has to access
整个矩阵 B。这就是我的观点。
the whole matrix B. That's my point.
因此，如果要在没有通信的情况下运行这个计算，
Therefore, to run this computation without communication,
矩阵B必须在所有设备上进行复制。
matrix B has to be replicated on all devices.
这同样可以通过这个块矩阵应用符号来说明，
And this can also be illustrated by this block matrix application notation,
其中C和A被分成四个块，而B则在所有设备上复制。
where C and A are split into four blocks where B are replicated on all devices.
明白了吗？有问题吗？很好，对吧？好的。
Okay? Any question? Good, right? Okay.
我们接下来会让它变得越来越复杂。
We're going to make it more and more complicated.
好，第二种情况基本上是并行化K循环，也就是归约循环。
Okay. The second case is basically to paralyze loop K, which is the reduction loop.
同样地，我们无法得出矩阵
Similarly, we can't derive that matrix
A必须按列分区，B必须分区的结论。
A has to be column protein and B has to be partin.
为什么？因为K是A和B的一个维度。
Why? Because K is a dimension of both A and B.
如果我们选择在K循环上分区，那么A和B都必须分区。
If we choose to part in loop K, then we have to part in both A and B.
好吗？为了得到C的结果，我们需要用到reduce，就像我说的，因为
Okay? To get the result of C, we need to use reduce, like I said, because after
这个通信设备只有部分和，需要用reduce把结果合并，得到C的结果。明白了吗。
this commutation device only have a partial sum, reduce the results to get the result C. Okay.
嗯，所以基本上我们需要用reduce来累加这些部分归约的结果。
Um, so basically we need to use reduce to accumulate, the partial reduction results.
最终的C会在所有设备上都有一份副本，因为reduce的结果就是这样。
And the final C is replicated on all devices because of it as a result of reduce.
好吗？这也可以用这个符号来说明。
Okay? This can also be illustrated by, this notation.
红色的符号，我想你们应该很熟悉，如果我用这种方式读出来，对吧？
The red notation, I think you are very familiar if I read it in this form, right?
我在A中取一部分，沿着这些列，
I part in A, following these columns,
我在B中取一部分，跟着我们，然后把它们加在一起。
I part in B, following us and just add them together.
每一部分的通信只发生在一个设备上。
And each part of communication happens only on one device.
好的，这基本上给你一些非常底层的，比如
Okay. This basically give you uh some very low level like
这是当我们并行化内存时的可视化展示。
visualization of what's going on when we paralyze memo.
我们也可以将两个循环一起并行化，事情会变得越来越复杂。
We can also paralyze two loops together, and things will become more and more complicated.
例如，我们可以并行化循环I和循环J，因为这两个循环不是归约循环，
For example, we can paralyze loop I and loop J because these two loops are not reduction loop,
所以我们不需要进行归约操作。
so we don't need or reduce.
如图所示。
As figure.
矩阵C既按列分区，也按行分区，被分成了四个区域，
Matrix C is both column partitioned and lo paritioned into four regions,
每个设备负责计算一个区域。
and each device is responsible for computing one region.
为了在不通信的情况下计算这个C，矩阵A和矩阵B需要进行部分切分。
In order to compute this C without communication, matrix A and matrix B how to be partially tiled.
那么你知道什么是部分切分吗？
So do you know what is partially tiled?
你首先将它分解成两部分，然后再进行切分。
You first decompose it into two parts and then you tie it.
好吗？我待会儿会给你一些阅读材料，但是我们稍后再深入讲一下这个。
Okay? And I will give you some reading material later, but uh, let's grind this a little bit later,
基本上，图片和B必须是部分平铺的矩阵A。
basically images and B have to be partially tiled matrix A is
矩阵A沿着行被分成两部分。
partitioned along the row into two parts.
第一部分会同时复制到设备一和设备B上。明白了吗？
The first part is replicated both on device one and device B. You got.
基本上我们用行分区的方式分割图片A，然后把上半部分复制到两个设备上，
Basically we part Images A using row party, and then we replicate the upper part onto two devices,
右半部分复制到另外两个设备上。
the right part into another two devices.
这就是我们在这里分割矩阵A的方式。
That is how we part matrix A here.
第二部分会被复制到设备三和设备四上。
The second part is wrap it on both device three and four.
通过这样存储A和B，我们基本上可以并行计算C，而不需要任何通信。
By storing A and B in this way, we can basically compute C in parallel without any communication.
对于矩阵B也是一样，我们首先把矩阵B按列分成两部分。
Same for matrix B, what do we do is basically we first column part in matrix B into two parts.
但这里我们有四个设备。
But here we have four devices.
我们在两个设备上处理eftter部分，在另外两个设备上处理wrap部分，这样我们就可以进行这个计算了。
We rap eftter part on two devices and wrap on another two devices, we can proceed this computation
没有问题，也不需要通信。
without problem no communication.
同样地，我们可以并行化循环I和循环K。结果是，
Similarly, we can parallelze both loop I and loop K. The results,
这基本上会产生部分平铺的输出C。嗯，因为我们并行化了循环K，
this basically results in partially tiled output C. Um, and because we parallelse loop K,
我们还需要一个操作来得到C。
we also need an use to get C.
好吗？你可以看到，呃，其实有很多变体，
Okay? And as you can see, uh, there are a lot of variants,
取决于你选择并行化哪个循环，以及你如何将循环映射到你的设备上，对吧？
depends on which loop you choose to paralyze and, and how you map the loops to your devices, right?
实际上，这个过程非常繁琐，嗯，要彻底梳理一遍。
And actually, it is very tedious, um, to basically go through this.
这确实很繁琐，可能性非常多，但并不是不可能。
It's very tedious. There are many many possibilities, but it's not impossible.
我只花了一天时间来钻研这个，好吗？
I just take a p like one day to grind this, okay?
我希望你也花点时间钻研一下这个。
And I hope you spend some time grind this.
对于这个二维备忘录，其实只有大约16种情况。
And for this two dimension memo, there are only like 16 cases.
是的，你基本上可以理解所有这些情况。
Yeah. And you can basically understand all these cases.
你可以把它们全部枚举出来，好吗？
You can enumerate them, okay?
但还有更难的，那就是，嗯，二维的列，好吗？
But there's something that even more difficult, that is um, column two D. Okay?
A其实就是之前的内容，对吧。
A is basically actually, it's before, right.
E基本上就是七重循环。
E is basically seven level for loop.
我们可以一个一个地描述这些循环。
And we can characterize loops one by one.
就像我说的，我之前做过这个。
So like I said, I think I did this before.
这是空间循环，非常简单。
This is the spatial loops, and it's very easy.
没有归约操作，所以你可以随意拆分它。
There's no reduction. So you can arbitrarily split it.
明白了吗？这些基本上是另一种模板计算循环，
Okay? And these are basically another stencil computton loop,
这基本上是在处理边界条件。
and um this is basically handling the boundary condition.
你需要非常小心，因为你要把卷积滤波器从左到右滑动，
You need to be very careful because you sliding the uh convolutional filter from left to right,
从上到下，并且你要处理边界条件，明白吗？
from up to bottom and you want to handle the boundary condition, okay?
显然，这个是最难的，因为它是一个归约循环，你需要在这个循环中累加
Apparently, this one is the most difficult because it is a reduction loop you are accumulating
结果。
results in this loop.
还有另外两个反应循环。
And another two reacting loops.
但你不需要并行化它，因为这是一个很小的反应，只有五个元素。
But you don't have to paralyze it because it's a very small reaction only five elements.
最常用的卷积实现方式是只使用一个小滤波器。
Be most convolutional two implement, you only use a small filter.
好的。为了并行化这个操作，你可以想象有多少种情况。
Okay. In order to paralyze this operator, you can imagine how many cases
你需要枚举很多种情况。
you need to enumerate a lot.
但我们不会这么做。
But we're not going to do this.
好的，没关系。是的，让我们继续。
Okay. It's fine. Yeah. Let's give.
好的，我觉得原因是
Okay. I think the reason
我之所以讲这些，是因为我首先想让你们明白，
I go through this is because I want to give you first,
我们是如何并行化一个单一操作的。
understanding how we paralyze a single operator.
本质上就是我们选择几个循环来并行化，
It's essentially like we choose a few loops to paralyze to
然后我们可以把每一部分分配到一个设备上。
partition and then we might each partito um a device.
由于我们的分区方式，会导致不同的通勤模式
And because of the way we partition, uh, it will result into different commuting patterns
和通信模式。明白了吗？
and communicating patterns. Okay?
到目前为止，你已经学会了如何并行化单个算子。
So so far, you have learned how to paralyze a single operator.
现在，让我们转到一个图上，看看一些例子。
Now, let us basically move to a graph and see some examples.
好吗？在这一页中，我们将展示数据并行实际上
Okay? So in this page, we all show that basically data partism is actually
是算子内并行的一种特殊情况。
a special case of intraoperatism.
我觉得我们之前做过这个，但我想再回顾一下。
I think we did this, but I just want to recap.
好吗？首先，我们会用图例来表示张量是
Okay? So first, we'll use legends to represent whether tensor
复制的、行并行的和列并行的，当然，我们还会用两种
is replicated row parison and common parison, of course, and we will use two types of
用于矩阵乘法的算子内并行策略。
intra parallel strategies for matm here.
好吗？嗯，所以类型一基本上就是我们沿着行对矩阵进行划分，对吧？
Okay? Um, so the type one is basically we partition the met along row, right?
如果你还记得这种类型一，我们不需要任何通信，对吧？好的。
If you still remember this type one, we don't need any communication, right? Okay.
因为如果我们选择这种类型一的划分，输入A会被划分，
Because if we choose this type one partitioning, the input A is partition and
输入B会被复制，然后我们会在结果矩阵上得到子块结果。
the input B is replicated and we get subaring results on the result matrix.
好的？类型B基本上是对内层循环的K进行划分，对吧？
Okay? The type B basically partitions, the inner loop reduction K, right?
所以如果我们做这种类型二的划分，那么类型二基本上就是
And so if we do this type two partitioning, then type two basically parting
沿着归约维度对两个输入都进行划分，嗯，这基本上要求完成这个计算，
both inputs along the reduction dimension, uh it basically requires finish this computation,
它需要一次归约操作，对吧？
it requires or reduce, right?
好的，现在我们来画一下两层MLP的图，对吧？
Okay. Now, let's draw them graph for two layer MLP, right?
这里是前向路径。
So here is a forward path.
湿的W一和W二基本上是复制的。这就是数据并行吗？
The wet W one and W two are basically replicated. This is data partism?
其他所有的通信，比如Mat Moss和Relu，
And all other communications such as Mat Moss and Relu,
它们都是沿着批次维度进行分区的。
um, they are partition along the batch dimension.
明白了吗？呃，没有通信。
Okay? Uh, there's no communication.
所以运行这个过程不需要通信。
So running this requires no communication.
然后我们画出反向传播的计算图，对吧？
Then we draw the backward graph, right?
现在，我把整个图展示给你看。
And now, I reveal the whole figure to you.
我在讲数据并行的时候做过这个。
I think I did this when I talk about data pism.
反向传播包括一种类型一的备忘录和类型二的备忘录。
Um, the backward pass consists of one type one memo and Type two memo.
对，一种类型一备忘录和两种类型二备忘录。
Right. One type one memo and two Type two memo. Okay.
嗯，所以在渐变上需要一些红色，这基本上和datapism是一样的。
Um, so it requires some reds on the gradients, and this is basically the same as datapism.
好吗？现在，我基本上把这个datapism通信连接到这个操作分区上。
Okay? Now, I basically connect this datapism communication to this operative partitioning.
现在你可以看到，Datapism之所以需要reduce，是因为我们
And now you can see, Datapism the reason dataparism requires reduce is because we
选择以这种方式对循环、metamo进行分区，对吧？
choose to partition the loop, the metamo in this way, okay?
等会儿我会给你展示很多其他的并行策略，
Later, I will show you a lot of other parallel strategies that they
它们基本上也都是像这样的特殊情况。
are basically just special cases like this.
所以基本上，我们就是在玩一个上色游戏，我们给操作符的不同区域上不同的颜色，
So basically, we're basically playing this coloring game, we give different color
这样就会导致不同的通信方式。
to different regions of the operator, and it will result into different communication.
好吗？有问题吗？
Okay? Any question?
很好，我们继续。
Cool. Let's continue.
好的。那么当你把这种内部算法应用到整个图上时，
Okay. So when you're applying this intra alismu for whole graph,
在边上会产生重新分区的通信成本。
there are repartitioning communication cost on the edges.
好的，我来解释一下。这是因为不同的算子并行策略可能需要
Okay, let me explain. This is because different operators paralyzing strategy might require
不同的分区格式来处理这些症状。
different partitioning formats of the symptoms.
所以我们需要进行重新分区或者重新分配。
So we need to do repartition or recharging.
我们还是以这个两层的MLP为例。
Let's still use this two layer MLP as an example.
考虑一下
Consider the edge between
Lu和第二个mano之间的边，就是那条较长的边。
Lu and the second mano, the longer edge.
这个al的分区格式，实际上是继承自前一个memo的分区格式。
The partitioning format of this al uh, follows the partitioning format of the previous memo.
基本上就是从那里继承过来的，明白吗？
It's basically inherent from there. Okay?
假设这个图，假设Lu是低分区。
Assuming this figure, assuming the Lu is low partition.
也就是说，我假设前面的图是低分区。
That is, I assume the previous graph was low partition.
好的。它基本上继承了分片，虽然是Lu，因为Lu
Okay. It basically inherits the sharding, although it's Lu because Lu
是按元素操作的，所以你什么都不用做。
is element wise, you don't have to do anything.
明白了吗？那么对于第二个备忘录，根据它选择的分区策略，
Okay? So for the second memo, um, depending on its chosen paten strategy,
类型一、类型二或类型三，它对输入的分区格式
type one or type two or type three, it may have a different requirement
可能有不同的要求。
of the input for the input partin format.
所以如果第二个备忘录也采用类型一的分区策略，
So if the second, meto also use a type one partitioning strategy,
就像我两页前展示的那样，对吧？
which I showed two slides before, right?
你沿着行进行分区。
You parting along the row.
好吗？如果你选择类型一的分区策略，
Okay? If you choose type one paren strategy,
那么这个Lu其实也需要是行分区，对吧？
then this Lu actually also needs to be row paten, right?
记住，在类型一中，第一个输入需要是行分区，第二个
Remember in type one, the first input need to be row partition and the second
输入需要是复制的。
input need to be replicated.
好吗？所以如果我们让这个备忘录选择类型一的分区策略，好，
Okay? So if we like this memo to choose the type one partin strategy, Okay, um,
我们发现这个rio实际上和之前的rival是匹配的。
We found that this rio actually matches with the previous rival.
它们都是行分区。
They are both row partition.
因此，这个是好的，因为你可以顺利地进行计算，没有任何问题。
Therefore, this one is good because you can proceed with the competon without any problem.
因为那个alo在每个设备上都有它需要的所有内容，好吗？
Because that alo has all the content it needed on each device, okay?
但是如果第二个Mdm使用了稍微不同的分区策略，比如这里的freedom。
But if the second Mdm use a slightly different par strategy, freedom here.
我选择了一种不同类型的策略。
I choose a different type of strategy.
我需要你复制这个u，但W的两个要作为列部分。
Well, I require this u to be replicated, but the W two to be column part.
好吗？在这种情况下，这个alo也需要被复制，对吧？
Okay? And in this case, this alo needs to be replicated, right?
这意味着两个设备都需要有Lu结果的副本。
Which means that both devices need to have a copy of the Lu results.
好吗？在这种情况下，你可以看到边变得有点不同。那么那条边是什么？
Okay? Uh, in this case, you can see the edge becomes a slightly different one. So what is that edge?
它是一个连接通信参数。
It is a connective communication parameter.
我想我讲完了。好的，没错，是all gather。
I think I cover. Okay. Yeah, it's all gather.
是的，所以如果你为不同的patina选择不同的策略，
Yeah. So in this way, if you choose different patina strategy for
对于不同的metamol，你会承担重新分区的成本，这种重新分区的成本会变成
different metamol you suffer a repartitioning cost, and this repartiting cost will become
一种连接许可的形式。
a format of a connective permissive. Okay.
在这个图中基本上都是聚合操作。
And in this figure is basically all gather.
好的，明白。那么为了最小化执行整个计算图的成本，
Okay. Cool. So in order to minimize the cost of executing the entire graph,
我们还需要为每个算子仔细选择策略，
we also need to carefully choose strategies for each operator to
以在设计整个新网络的分区策略时最小化这种重分区的成本。
minimize this repartining cost when we design our partin strategy for the entire new network.
这就是我想表达的重点。简单回顾一下，对吧？
That's the point I want to make. Just to recap, right?
所以我认为现在你基本上可以枚举所有可能的通信成本，
So I think now you can basically enumerate all the possible communicating costs
当你进行重分区时，对吧？
when you do recharging, right?
我觉得你们对这个图已经非常熟悉了。
I think you guys are very familiar with this figure already.
嗯，重分区基本上就像我们让你去交换张量的着色方案一样，对吧？
Um, repartitioning is basically like we ask you to swap the coloring scheme of the tensors, right?
而且根据你想怎么交换，基本上就会引入连接原语。
And depending on how you want to swap, you basically introduce connective primitive.
好的。好的，我们来总结一下让你图中所有算子并行化的问题，好吗？
Okay. Okay, let's summarize the problem of paralyzing all the operators in your graph, okay?
所以，给定一个图，对于每个算子，都有多种并行化策略，对吧？
So given a graph, for each operator, there are multiple paralyzing strategies for it, okay?
我们的目标是为每个算子选择一种并行策略，这样我们就可以
And our goal is to pick one parallel strategy for each operator so that we can
最小化整个图的执行成本。
minimize the cost of executing the entire graph.
明白了吗？所以我现在基本上把这个问题表述为一个优化问题。
Does that make sense? So I'm basically stating this problem as an optimization now.
好吗？你需要为每个节点选择一种着色方案，然后枚举
Okay? You want to pick a coloring scheme for each node, and then you enumerate
所有可能的通信成本，并且你要最小化这个成本。
all the possible commuting costs and you want to minimize that cost.
这样基本上就能让你的图运行得更快，对吧？
That will basically make your graph run fast. Okay?
所以成本基本上包括节点成本和边的成本。
So the cost basically consists of the node cost and the edge cost.
节点成本主要是计算和通信成本。
Okay? The node cost are basically computation and communication cost.
因为当你选择的时候，当你选择某种特定类型的鸽子时，你已经有了一些成本。
Because when you choose, when you choose a particular type of pigon you already have some cost.
你选择第二类型的妈妈鸽子，你有或者减少了成本。
You choose type two mama paig you have or reduce.
对，好的。第二个成本是边缘情况。
Right. Okay. And the second cause is edge case.
也就是说，你为那个节点选择了蛋白质策略，为第二个节点选择了蛋白质单元。
That is, you choose protein srgy for that node, and you choose protein unit for second node.
并且因为第一个节点的输出和第二个节点的输入不是完全一致的。
And because of the sharing of the first node, output and the second nodes input are not all green.
所以你遇到了边缘情况。
So you're suffering edge case.
也就是说，你需要重新分片，而这个分片以连接的形式出现。
That is, you need to reshare and that shard comes at a form of connecting.
因此，如果你想写下这个问题，基本上就是，
Therefore, if you want to write down this problem is basically,
嗯，就是那个公式，节点成本加上边缘成本。
um, that equation, node cost plus edge cost.
边缘成本是剩余成本，节点成本是特定类型本身的成本。
Edge cost is a resting cost and nod cost is a cost inherent to the specific type of
你选择的分区策略就是我们的p。好的。
parting strategy you choose for our p. Okay.
现在我觉得你大致明白怎么解这道题了，对吧？
And now I think you roughly have an idea how to solve this question, right?
解决这个问题的一个简单方法就是，枚举所有的可能性。
One easy way to solve this problem is basically, you enumerate all the possibilities.
你不断地枚举图中的内容，基本上就是枚举每一种类型、每一种可能性，
You keep enumeraating the graph, and you basically enumeraating every type every possibility,
看你怎么划分操作符。
how you can partition operator.
一旦你确定了所有操作符的划分方式，
And once you lock down a possibility of the partitioning of all the operators,
基本上你就可以推导出所有的代价，对吧？
you basically can't derive all the cost, right?
你写下来，因为你选择了这个方案，会产生多少连接通信。
You write down, how many connective communication
基本上，然后你就开始优化，试着找出
I incurred because I choose this.
更好的方案。
And basically, then you start optimizing right you try to figure out
基本上就是成本最低的那个。
the one that basically has the lowest cost.
好的，这基本上就是内部并行。
Okay. That is basically intraparism.
明白了吗？它和外部并行有点不同。
Okay? It is slightly different from Inter.
还记得在外部并行中，我们的目标是最小化气泡数。
Still remember in Inter, our goal is to minimize bubbles.
谁能安排一个最小化气泡的调度，我们还要确保各个阶段是等价的。
Who a schedule that minimize bubbles, and we want to make sure the stages are equivalent.
明白了吗？但在内部并行中，基本上就是这个公式。明白了吗？
Okay? But in Intra is basically this equation. Okay?
有什么问题吗？很好。希望你明白了，好吗？
Any question? Cool. I hope you get it, okay?
如果你还不明白，希望你能花更多时间理解这些幻灯片，好吗？
If you don't I hope you spending more time understanding the slides, okay?
这非常重要，因为一旦你理解了数学原理，你就能理解
And this is very important because once you understand mathematics, you will be able to understand
今天所有人发明的并行方法。
all the partisan people invented today.
好吗？他们所做的基本上就是试图最小化这个成本。
Okay? What they are doing is basically try to minimize this cost.
好吗？所以为了解决这个问题，人们采用了各种各样的解决方案，
Okay? So to solve this problem, people have used various solutions,
包括手动设计、随机搜索、
including, manual design, randomized search,
动态规划和整数线性规划。
dynamic programming, and the integer linear programming.
正如我所说，他们基本上是在优化服务器来解决这个问题。
As I said, they are basically the optimizing servers to solve this problem.
好吗？我会展示一些非常有代表性的解决方案。
Okay? And I will show a few solutions which are very notable.
好的。我首先会介绍一些为特定节点手动设计的策略，
Okay. I will first introduce some strategies that are manually designed for specific notes,
包括AlexNet、Makaton RM和THR MOE。
including AlexNet Makaton RM and THR MOE.
AlexNet是深度学习的开端，对吧？
AlexNet is the beginning of deep learning, right?
Macron RM是为媒体设计的，好吗？每天都在用。
Macron RM is the one for media, okay? Use every day.
TR 是谷歌推出的一个系统。
TR is a one by Google.
好吗？我还介绍了几个基本上为此设计的系统。
Okay? As well I introduced several systems that basically, designed for this.
好吗？所以从现代深度学习一开始，人们就开始使用分区方法。
Okay? So right from the beginning of modern deep learning, um, people start using intra partism.
好吗？Alex 就是一个很好的例子。
Okay? Um, Alex a good example.
这张图引用自 Axon 论文，对吧？
This figure was quoted from Axon paper, right?
我在第一节课上也展示过这张图，好吗？
And I also showed this figure in my first lecture, okay?
基本上在这张图中，你可以看到，作者试图传达一个想法，
Um so basically in this figure, you can see, the author tries to convey a idea where
即每一层都被分区，每一层的部分分布在不同的设备上，好吗？
the layer was partitioned and each layer has a part, acute different uh on different devices, okay?
基本上它把一个分组卷积分成两部分，并将它们对齐到 GPU 上，
And basically it partitions a group convolution, uh into two parts and align them to GPS
这让 Alexa 能够提升 top-1 的准确率。
this enables Alexa to basically increase the top one accuracy.
呃，EB净值上几乎上涨了2%。
Uh, buy almost like 2% on EB net.
但这样做只是因为你家里有很多人一起训练。
But just doing this because you home multi people who train.
一个更近的例子基本上是Microtron RM，这是一个给定的阅读材料。
E. A more recent example is basically Microtron RM, and this is a given reading.
我觉得在这一点上，你们已经理解那篇论文了。
I think at this point, you guys already understand that paper.
但我想做的是，我基本上试图画出
But what I try to do is I basically try to draw
那篇论文中的策略和
the connection between the strategies in that paper and,
我在数学建模中解释的内容之间的联系。
what I explained in the mathematical modeling.
好吗？所以基本上，它用intraoperatism来训练语言模型，
Okay? So basically, it used intraoperatism to train the language models,
并且它设计了一种非常具体的策略来并行化transformer中的MLP和数学注意力机制。
and it designs a very specific strategy to paralyze the MLP and math attention in the transformer.
所以在这里，嗯，我基本上展示了论文中的图三，说明如何并行化MLP。
So here, um, I basically show the figure three from the paper on how to paralyze the MLP.
嗯，如果你读过论文，类似的处理也应用在多头注意力机制上。
Um, and a similar stretch is also applied to the multi head attention if you read a paper.
好吗？这些图看起来非常非常复杂。
Okay? These figure looks very very complicated.
一旦你理解了我们的模型，我们就可以简化它。
And we can simplify it once you understand our model.
没有成本和边缘成本。那么该如何简化呢？
No cost and edge cost. So how to simplify it.
基本上，对于这个两层的MLP，我们无法进行数据并行，因为权重矩阵太大了。
Basically for this two layer MLP, we cannot do data parison because the weight matrix is too large.
为了在最小化通信成本的同时进行分区，
To partition it while minimizing the communication cost,
我们可以将第一个权重矩阵按列分区，第二个按行分区。
we can make the first weight matrix column partition and the second row partition.
通过这样做，我们在前向传播时只需要做一次归约，
And by doing this, we only need to do one or reduce during the forward and
在反向传播时再做一次归约。
another reduced during backward.
好的，这基本上就是我们对microtome论文的可视化。
Okay. This is basically our visualization for the microtome paper.
这样说有道理吗？可以吗？
Does this make sense? Okay?
可以。如果你只是试着解析这个图，你会发现我们基本上只需要用到这些。
Yeah. And if you just read try to parse the graph, you can see, we basically just have to use.
好的。嗯，需要注意的是，有些计算比如dropout
Okay. Yeah. Um, and note that some compution such as dropout
是被重复的，因为dropout的计算量其实很小。
are replicated because dropout is pretty minimal.
好的，所以我们只需要把它们复制一下就行了。
Okay, so we just need to replicate them.
好的？但这样做的成本其实很低。
Okay? But this is pretty affordable, yeah.
好的。而且现在，这种策略有一个名字。
Okay. And today, this strategy has a lame.
它被称为tenser Perl。
It's called tenser Perl.
好的。如果你去任何一个库，比如
Okay. If you go to any library like
VOMhuinf、deep speed、microphones，都叫tenser Barrel。
VOMhuinf deep speed microphones called tenser Barrel.
它基本上就是这样描述的。
And it's essentially described.
好的，好的。现在你了解了Megatro RM。
Okay. Okay. Now, you understand Megatro RM.
另一个例子基本上是G hard MOE，这个hard MOE基本上是
Another example is basically G hard MOE, this hard MOE is basically
所谓per parallel的第一个发明者。
the first inventor of the so called per parallel.
这是一种在MOE模型中划分专家的新策略，
Okay. It is a new strategy for partitioning experts in MOE model,
我将在下一节课讲解这个内容。
and I'm going to cover the next lecture.
Per parallel基本上是实现Deepi with three的关键技术。
Okay. Per parallel is basically the key technology enables Deepi with three.
好的？我会再次展示论文中的图，说明如何并行化
Okay? Again, I will show the figure from the paper on how to paralyze
模型，你可以看到这个图非常复杂。
model you can see this figure is very complicated.
然后，我将用我们的符号来简化它。
And uh I'm going to simplify it using our notation.
基本上，这篇论文所做的就是针对普通的transformer层，
So basically what this paper is doing is basically for the normal transformer layers,
它基本上进行数据并行，这很直接。
it basically does data paring which is straightforward.
所以基本上权重会被复制，用于普通层。
So basically the weights, and basically replicate it for the normal layers.
但对于MOE层，我们会在专家维度上对权重和批量矩阵进行分区。
But for the MOE layers, we partition the weights and the batch met along the expert dimension.
这样可以最小化通信量。
And this minimize the communication.
你还可以回头枚举所有可能的分区方式。
And you can go back and enumerate all possible partition.
这是能够最小化通信量的分区方式。
This is the one that minimize the communication.
你可以看到专家设计确实是专家设计。
Okay. And you can see expert design is indeed expert design.
对吧？是的，有很多增强方法。
Okay? Yeah, a lot of augmentation.
而且在普通层和MOE层之间切换时，我们需要进行通信。
And to switch between the normal layers to the MOE layers, we need a communication.
那么这里的通信是什么？让我来强调一下。
So what is the communication? Let me highlight it.
那么这里的通信是什么？
So what is the communication here?
什么？是在这里。
Sorry? It's at.
对，基本上是自动的。
Yeah. It's basically auto.
好的，这样说得通吧？
Okay. Makes sense, right?
因为我们在交换分区的维度。
Because we are swapping the partitioning dimension.
所以这就是为什么是自动的。
So that's why it's auto.
现在你明白为什么deep sig在实现一个非常非常快的auto上花了很多精力，
Now, you understand why deep sig inte a lot of effort on implementing a really,
auto其实非常小，因为你想在维度上进行分区，
really fast auto auto is super small, because you want to partition in dimension,
你就必须用Auto，而且这一切都需要非常快，否则就会出问题，明白吗？
you have to do Auto and that's all need to be fast otherwise sonal, okay?
很好，你明白了。在这次作业中，
Cool. You get it. In this homework,
我让你实现auto，但我从没要求你一定要用它，
I ask you to implement auto, but I never ask you to use it
因为在作业的第三部分，
because in the third part of the homework,
我让你基本上用你写的auto来实现Tinder Parl，就是让你做这个。
I ask you to basically use or reduce you write to Tinder Parl which is this one ask you to do this.
但是在下一次作业的第一个任务中，你就要做这个了。
But in the next homework, the first assignment, you're going to do this.
基本上你要用你自己的auto来实现这部分内容。
Basically you use your own auto to implement this part.
好的。好的。所以这一页幻灯片对你完成
Okay. Okay. So this slide is pretty important for you to finish the alignment,
下一次作业的第一个对齐问题非常重要。
first problem of the next homework.
好的，很棒。
Okay. Cool.
好的。
Okay.
有什么问题吗？这两种基本上是最常用的内部并行策略。
Any question. These two are basically the most used intra parallel strategy.
我再重复一遍，张量并行，基本上就是把矩阵分区。
Let me repeat again, ten parallel, where basically you partition
两个权重矩阵分别在不同的行、列进行分区，这样你就会有一次通信或减少一次通信。
the two weed matrix follow in different one row, column, and you incur one or reduce.
另一种是专家并行，基本上就是把分区
Another is expert parallel, where you basically partition
补丁矩阵按照MOE的专家维度分区，但在普通层做数据并行。
the patch met follow the expert dimension at the MOE, but you do data parallel at the normal layers.
当你从第一种并行切换到第二种并行时，你会产生一次自动通信。
And when you switch from the first party to the second parity you incur auto.
好，这就是基本思路。
Okay. That is the idea.
明白了吗？现在我要介绍第三种并行方式。
Okay? Now I'm going to introduce a third part of interop.
它叫做Zero优化器。
It's called zero optimor.
这个是由Deep Speed团队发明的，也是其中之一。
This one was invented by Deep Speed Team, this one is also one of
最常用的优化器、参数划分策略。
the most used um optimizer, parting strategy.
在岩石学中，你会想给它取一个不同的名字。
In petrology you want to find a different name for it.
它被称为FSDP，全称是完全共享数据并行。
It's called FSDPFully shared data parallel.
但本质上，他们的机制基本上是基于这个Zero Optimizer。让我来解释一下。
But essentially, their mechanism is basically based on this zero opmeor. Let me explain.
基本上，这个项目叫做
So basically, uh, this project is called
Zero Optimizer，它是一种数据并行的内存优化方法。
Zero oppmentar and it's a memory oppmentation, um, of data datapoism.
回想一下，在数据并行中我们会复制模型权重，对吧？
So recall in datapoism we replicate motor ways, right?
但这并不是我们复制的唯一内容。
Um but this is not the only thing we replicate.
比如说，当我们选择使用那个Adam优化器时，
So for example, when we choose to use that atom Oppener, um,
当我们进行这种混合精度训练时，
uh, when we do this kind of mixed precision training,
我们还需要存储FP32主副本，对吧？
we also need to store FP 32 master copy, right?
我还记得在内存讲座中，我们还需要存储所有那些优化器状态，
I still remember in memory lecture, we also need to store all those optimal states,
一阶和二阶矩，也都是以LP32高精度存储的。
first and second moments, which are also stored in LP 32 high precision.
明白了吗？而且这些来自优化器的辅助状态实际上比LP16权重大得多。
Okay? And this auxiliary states from optimor actually is much larger than LP 16 weights.
它占用了大量内存。
It takes a lot of memory.
我希望你还记得那个系数。
I hope you still remember the factor.
对于Adam优化器来说，它需要12倍的系数，对吧？
So for the atom Opmeor it takes a factor of 12, right?
而对于其他的，只需要4倍的系数。
And for the rest, it only take a factor of four.
也就是说，是权重和梯度的三倍。
Okay, it's three times the weight and gradients.
为了解决这个问题，这篇论文提出将所有这些张量进行分区，
Okay? And to solve this problem, this paper proposed to partition all these sensors,
好的，分为三个阶段。
okay, into three stages.
好的，这个表基本上展示了内存使用和通信成本。
Okay. Uh This table basically shows, the memory usage and communicating cost of
一个是在数据并行下，另外三个阶段是他们的优化方法。
one in a data parallel and three stages of their oppumentu.
好吗？而且这个表也是今天最重要的幻灯片之一，好吗？
Okay? And this table is one of the most important slides today as well, okay?
你之后应该好好理解这个内容。
And you should internalize this later.
好的，这对你分析FSDP时的成本会非常有帮助，好吗？
Okay. And this will be super helpful for you to analyze the cost when you do FSDP, okay?
嗯，这里我来介绍一下符号表示方法。
Um, and here, basically, let me introduce a notation.
设M为参数数量，N为设备数量。
So let M be the amber parameters and M be the ambo devices.
你将要进行并行计算。
You are going to perform parallelism.
好的，假设我们使用
Okay? Um assuming we use
Atom优化器使用LP 16混合精度训练，优化器状态需要多少？
Atom optimizer with LP 16 mixed precision training, the optimeor states, it takes how many?
12，对吧？我已经重复很多很多次了。好，你需要记住。
12, right? I repeat this many, many times. Okay. You need to remember.
梯度是2，对吧？
The gradients is two, right?
因为是PC 16，对吧？
Because it's PC 16, right?
是两个字节，这就是2的原因。
It's two bytes. That's what two.
模型也是2，因为它也是2。
The model is two, because it's also two.
好的。所以，如果你进行数据并行，基本上你是在说，
Okay. Therefore, if you do data partism, sically you are saying,
我会在所有设备上复制全部内容，只在batch维度上进行切分。
I'm going to replicate all on all devices only partision along the badge dimension.
因此，每个设备的内存消耗基本上是16。
Therefore, the memory cost of each device is basically 16.
这样说有道理吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，你会复制所有内容，对吧？
Okay, you replicate everything, right?
那通信成本是多少呢？
And what's the communicating cost?
我已经解释过很多很多次了，
I already explained many many times,
在数据划分中，通信成本基本上就是所有权重的全量归约。
In data partism the communing cost is basically all reduced of the weights.
因此，都是全量归约。
Therefore, it's all reduced to.
并且根据你选择在哪个阶段应用Zero，
And depending on the stages you choose to apply zero,
你实际上是在划分不同的部分。
you are essentially partitioning different parts of this.
在Zero第一阶段，你选择在最优状态下划分。
In zero stage one, you choose to parti in optimal states.
在Zero第二阶段，你选择划分可选状态和参数，在第三阶段，
In zero stage two, you choose to partition optional states and ingredients, and in stage three,
你全部划分，根据你的划分方式，通信量也会不同。
you pi in all and depending on how you partition it, you will incur different communication,
接下来我会帮你一起梳理这个过程。
which I will help you go through next.
但现在，假设你已经了解了这个划分方式，我们可以推导出内存消耗
But now, assume you already know this petition, we are able to derive the memory cost
和通信消耗，对吧？
and communicating cost, right?
所以我们先跳过通信消耗，因为我还需要解释一下。
So maybe let's skip communicating cost first because I need to explain it.
但内存消耗其实很容易理解，对吧？
But for memory it's very easy to understand, right?
如果你划分了各种状态，但没有划分参数和模型权重，
So if you're part various states but not partying ingredients and model ways,
那么每个设备的内存基本上就是这两部分会被复制。
then your per device memory is basically these two will be replicated.
这里有一个四倍的项。
There is a term of four.
但这一部分会在所有N个设备之间分割。
But this one is partition across all N devices.
所以每个设备只需要存储12除以
Therefore, each device only need to stor 12 divided by
N。这基本上就是01的内存开销。
N. This is basically the memory cost of 01.
同样地，你可以做完全一样的事情，不断地堆叠更多，
Similarly, you can do exactly the same thing that you keep piting more and more,
然后你基本上就是把这两个项的开销摊到所有设备上。
and then you are basically amortize these two terms across all devices.
这就是为什么在第三阶段，每个设备只需要存储16除以
That's why in sty three, each device only need to store 16 divided by
N。相比于datapat，这是一个很大的内存节省。
N. That's a big memory saving compared to datapat.
好的。你也知道，基本上零阶段、一阶段、二阶段、
Okay. And you also know that basically, the difference between zero stage one, two,
三阶段，它们本质上就是这两种。
three, they are essentially like these two.
好的。最重要的部分就像我说的，是操作状态，因为有一个12。
Okay. And the big part is, like I said, operal state because there's a 12.
好的。现在你明白数学原理了。
Okay. Okay. Now, you understand the math.
我们来逐步看看每个阶段。
Let's go through each stage.
我们来试着理解一下这个通信。
Let's try to understand the communication.
有什么问题吗？好，再说一个词。
Any question? Okay. One more word.
所以如果你用FSDP，就是全共享数据桶，基本上就是这个。
So I petric if you do FSDP that is fully shaded data Barrels basically this one.
这里会说有三个，这叫全共享数据桶。
There will say three. It's called fully shaded data Barrel.
这里的“全”意思是所有东西都共享。明白了吗？
That fully means everything is shared. Okay.
好吧？这样有助于你记住。
Okay? To help you remember.
好，我们来看一下zero是怎么做的，好吗？
Okay, let's see what zero does, okay?
zero的核心思想是用reduce scatter和gather来替换或减少操作。
So the key idea of zero is to replace or reduce with reduce scatter and or gather.
这个公式，你还记得吧？
Okay? This equation, help you still remember, right?
我在集体通信那部分讲过这个。
I covered this in collective communication.
好的，让我更改一下我的密码。
Okay, let me change my pin.
好的，所以左侧和右侧的通信成本是一样的。
Okay. So the left hand side and the right hand side have the same communicating cost.
但通过这种分解，我们可以划分出更多的复制答案和计算。
But by doing this decomposition, we can partition more replicate answers and computations.
这里是Wanina数据对比。
So here is Wanina data parison.
它运行或归约以累积部分结果，也就是部分梯度，我刚才说过。
And it runs or reduce to accumulate partial results, partial gradients, I said
其他方式和opener状态也是被复制的。
that other ways and opener states are replicated.
这就是为什么这个图看起来是这样的。
That's why this graph looks like this.
好吗？不，我已经把视角放大到opener部分了。
Okay? No, I already zoom into the opener part.
好的，我忽略了前向和反向部分。
Okay, I ignore the forward and backward part.
好的，所以我们从部分梯度开始，因为我们沿着一行进行划分。
Okay. So here we start with a partial gradient because we part in along a row.
在反向推荐之后，每个设备都有一个部分梯度。
And after the backward recommendation, each device has a partial gradient.
但正如我所说，在数据并行中，我们会复制所有内容，包括open mender的状态，对吧？
But as I said, in data parism we replicate everything, including open mender states, right?
为了让open miner进行计算，我们发现会有一个重启的开销，对吧？
In order for the open miner to compute, we find that there's a there's a restarting cost, right?
这个opium需要在HDS上有完整的成分副本，因为它是被复制的。
This opium need a full copy of ingredients on HDS because it's replicated.
但一开始，我们只有一部分。
But at the beginning, we only have a partile.
因此，这一切都被归约了。
Therefore, this is all reduced.
好吗？但这很合理，这就是数据并行，好吗？
Okay? But that makes sense This is data partism, okay?
那么02是什么？在错误二中，基本上是用reduced scatter替换或归约操作，好吗？
So what is 02? In error two, um, it basically replace or reduce with reduced scatter. Okay?
所以，结果是，基本上就是这样。
So the result of, um, so basically here.
在R2中，我们说我们要对所有operar状态进行分区，对吧？
In R two, we said that we are going to partition all the operar states, right?
因此，open states 这种动量就像是一阶、二阶矩一样。
Therefore, open states this momentum like first, second moment,
它们在 batch 维度上进行了分区。
they partisonFolloing in the batch dimension.
在这里，在 S2 中，它被替换或用 reduced scatter 来简化了。
And here in S two, it replaced or reduced with reduced scatter here.
reduced scatter 的结果仍然是分区的。
The result or reduced scatter is still partitioned.
因为后续的大多数计算都是按元素进行的，
Because most of the later competon are element wise,
这些计算可以在分区格式下完成。
the computation can be done on partition format.
没问题。也就是说，open states 是分区的，每个分区只执行自己的计算。
No problem. That is open states are patina and each partin only perform its own competition.
这样是可以的，没问题。
It's fine. Okay.
但在某些时候，我们需要以分区格式存储梯度和 open states。
But at some point, we need to store the gradits and open states in parison format.
但正因为如此，对吧，记住这个因素。
But because of this, right, remember this factor.
我们从中获得了好处，对吧？
We have a benefit of this, right?
所以这些开放状态基本上是在所有设备之间摊销的。
So the open states are basically amortized across all devices.
好的，嗯，这样可以减少内存成本。
Okay. Um, and this reduce the memory cost.
在每次更新后，我们基本上可以使用它们或者收集。
And after always updated, we can basically use them or gather.
以获得下一次迭代所需的复制宽度。
To get the replicate width for the next iteration.
然后我们继续进行计算。
Then we proceed to competation.
实际上，我们的做法是每一层都这样做。
In reality, what we do is we do this per layer.
每次进入一层时，我们发现，呃，抱歉，其实不是每一层。
Every time we go to one layer, we find that um uh sorry, it's not per layer.
是03，三，我们是按层处理的。
It's 03, three, we do it per layer.
但对于这个操作状态，一旦我们进入操作状态计算，
But for this in opera state, that is once we proceed into the operar state competition,
我们发现任何需要重新充电的地方，我们都会进行充电。
we find anything that is require recharging, we will perform recharging.
如果你做一下分析，你会发现本质上我们基本上是在
If you do the um, analysis, you'll find that essentially we are basically
分解或者简化为简化的调度和收集器。
decomposing or reduce into reduced schedule and getter.
如果你比较上面的图和下面的图，你会发现通信
If you compare the upper graph and lower graph, you'll find that the communicating
成本是完全一样的，因为all reduce等于reduce scatter加上orgather，对吧？
cost is exactly the same, because all reduce equals to reduce scatter plus or gather, right?
在这个图中，你做了一次reduce。
In this graph, you do one reduce.
在这个图中，你做了reduce scatter加上orgather。
In this graph, you do reduce scatter plus orgater.
但是内存表现要好得多。
But the memory is much better.
在第二个图中，所有的操作数状态都是分区的。
In the second graph, all the operant states they are partition.
但在第一个图中，它们是复制的。
But in the first graph, they are replicated.
这是零C二阶段。
This is zero C two.
现在让我们看看如何划分更多阶段、更多张量，以实现零C三阶段。
And now let's try to see how we can partition more stages, more tensors to get zero C three.
这里仍然是零C二阶段。
Here is still zero C two.
基本上，权重还是被复制的，对吧？
Basically, um, the widths are still replicated, right?
在零阶段二中，我们只划分了梯度和操作状态。
I zero stage two, we only partition the um, gradients and the operant states.
权重还是被复制的，因为前向传播
The widths are still replicated because both forward
和反向传播都需要完整的权重副本，
and backward requires a full copy of the weights,
所以我们复制权重以减少通信量。
so we replicate the weights to reduce the communication.
但如果模型太大，我们也可以划分权重，从而实现零阶段三。
But if the model is too large, we can also part in the width, as well to get zero stage three.
如你所见，与零S二和零阶段三相比，
As you can see, compared to zero S two and zero stage three,
我们要做的是继续对这些权重进行分区。
what do we do is we continue to part in these weights.
好的。在这两个里面，我们复制宽度。
Okay. Here in those two, we replicate the width.
但我说过，这个宽度会非常大。
But I said, this width is going to be pretty big.
比如说，当你GB真的很大时。
For example, when you GB really is big.
你也想对它进行分区。
You also want to partition it.
那你怎么分区呢？
And what's your partition it?
因为在规范竞赛期间，你需要这个是一个完整的副本，就像这样。
Because during the spec competition, uh, you require this one to be a full copy like this.
所以为了从这里恢复到这里，你要做的基本上是全部一起执行。
So in order to recover from here to here, what do you do is basically you perform all together.
而且你可以逐层进行这个操作。
And you can do this layer by layer.
这是因为你的权重现在已经被分区了，对吧？
That is because your weight is is partion now, right?
然后你进入一层，并且你会发现这些层在所有设备上进行了分区。
And you proceed to one layer and you find the layers with partition across all devices.
但为了进行前向计算，你必须获得完整的宽度。
But in order to compute the forward, you have to get the full version of the width.
你需要做的是执行一次gather操作来获得宽度，然后继续进行计算。
What do you do is you perform an gather to get the width, and you proceed to commutation.
一旦你完成计算，就进入下一层，然后
And once you finish computation, you proceed to the next layer and you
丢弃之前gather的结果。
throw away the or gather results.
你仍然会在你的设备上保留一份分片。
You still preserve one chart on your device.
好的，总结一下，区别在于
Okay. To summarize, the difference
02-03基本上是在内存和通信之间做权衡。
02-03 is basically a trade off between memory and communication.
所以如果你想升级到02-03，你会看到需要更多的内存，
So if you want to upgrade 02-03, you are going to see be more memory,
但你需要为一次gather操作付出通信的代价。
but you are going to pay the cost of one or gather.
这就是为什么03的通信成本是1.5个ordos。
That's why the communicating cost of 03 is 1.5 ordos.
因为减少了Gater和orgaeryeach，基本上是减少了一半的redos。有问题吗？
Because reduce Gater and orgaeryeach basically half or redos. Any question?
好的，让我来整合一下这个理解。
Okay. Let me consolidate this understanding.
我想我已经解释了这四种不同模式在内存成本上的区别，
I think I explained the difference between all these four different paten the memory cost,
现在你明白了，其实就是在这个上面再加一个。
now you understand it is basically putting one more into the upper part of this one.
现在你明白了通信成本。
Now you understand the community cost.
在数据并行中，通信成本被降低了。
In dataparism community cost is reduced.
在第12阶段，通信成本基本上是把这个reduce分解为
In stage 12, the commuting cost is basically decomposing this reduced
reduce setter和orgether，是一样的。
into reduced setter and orgether, it's the same.
但如果我们继续演化到03，我们会再引入一个orgether。
But if we continue to evolve into 03, we are introduced one more orgether.
这是1.5个红色的。
It's 1.5 reds.
是的。有什么理由要用这个吗？
Yeah. Reason to use one?
很好的问题。01已经基本没人用了。
Very good question. 01 is already like no one use that.
是的。为什么？因为如果你比较这两个数字，通信成本是一样的。
Yeah. Why? Because if you compare these two numbers, communication cost is the same.
但是zero C two能节省更多内存。
But zero C two saves more memory.
是的。所以现在大家都是从02开始的。
Yeah. So today, people start with 02.
好吗？这个非常重要，我觉得这会让你有很多相关的阅读材料，
Yeah. Okay? Okay, this is very important, and I think that give you a lot of reading on this,
你应该把那些阅读内容和这个例子结合起来，
and you should connect those readings to this illustration,
我认为这会提升你的理解。
and I think it will enhance your understanding.
好，下一个项目基本上就是匹配tender flow。
Okay. Next project is basically match tender flow,
这是谷歌开发的一个用于编写模型并行TensorFlow程序的系统。
It is a system developed by Google for writing model parallel tender flow programs.
这里的关键思想基本上是通过指定Pagen策略来实现。
And the key idea here is basically specify the Pagen strategy by
具体做法是将张量的维度映射到匹配的维度上。
mapping tenser dimension to match dimensions.
下面是一个代码示例。
So here is a code example.
用户需要使用这个特殊的API来编写程序。
User need to use this special API for writing programs.
在代码中，用户会为每个张量维度和每个匹配维度指定一个标签。
And in the code, users give every tensor dimension a lime and
那么，什么是mash呢？
every match dimension lime. So what is mash?
Mash基本上是一个由设备组成的矩阵，
So Mash is basically a matrix of devices arranged,
例如，可以排列成二维的形式，对吧？
for example, arranged in like two dimension, okay?
用户定义了一个映射，将张量的维度映射到匹配的维度上。
And, um the user defined a mapping that basically maps the tinder dimension to match dimension.
然后系统基本上会生成一个并行的Tinder流图
And the system will basically generate a paralyzed tinder flow graph
按照专门的映射方式，明白吗？
following the specialized mapping, okay?
而且这个系统需要重写整个程序。
And this system requires a rewriting of the whole program.
所以它不是很友好，后来被另一个系统取代了，明白吗？
So it is not very user friendly and later it was replaced by another system, okay?
这个GSMPDPMD基本上被认为是Messenger Flow的继任者。
And this is GSMPDPMD is basically considered as a successor of the messenger flow.
它采用了非常类似的基于编译器的方法，但它生成了那个想法，明白吗？
It follows a very similar compiler based approach, but it generates that idea, okay?
用户不需要编写整个流图。
User do not need to write the whole graph.
相反，他们只需要插入一些标记来指定并行策略
Instead, they just insert some notations to specify the parallel strategy
针对某些重要的张量。
of certain important tensors.
后续编译器会自动将并行策略传播到整个流图
And later the compiler will basically propagate the partntrategy to the whole graph
并为整个计算图生成一个分区策略。
and generate a partons strategy for the entire graph.
这里有一些自动化的内容。
There are some automation here.
好的。最后我想指出，intraop 和 interop 应该结合起来。
Okay. And last, I want to point out that intraop and interop, they should be combined.
明白吗？因为这两种并行方式之间存在权衡，我们可以
Okay? Because there are trade offs between these two kinds of parisms and we can
结合它们来利用这种权衡，从而获得最佳性能。
combine them to exploit the trade off and achieve the optimal performance.
好的？这是计算图，对吧？
Okay? Here is the computer graph, right?
然后，我们把它切分成四个阶段。
And, which we slice into four stages.
好的。我们不再把一个阶段分配到一个设备上，
Okay. And instead of assigning a stage on one device,
而是可以把每个阶段分配到一个设备网格上。
we can basically assign each stage to a to a device mesh.
也就是一组设备。比如说，我们可以把四个 GPU 分配给第一个阶段。
A group of devices. And, um, for example, we can add four GPUs to ask you the first stage,
两个GB是第二阶段，六个GB是第三阶段，两个GB是第一阶段。
two GBs second stage, and six GB the third stage, and two GB first stage.
那为什么要这么做呢？原因其实很简单，就像我刚才说的，
So why would do this? Reason is pretty simple because like I said,
在流水线并行中，你要确保每个阶段的执行时间是一样的。
in Pipeline parism you want to make sure the ascuon time of which stage is the same.
所以，如果你的神经网络结构是异构的，也就是说各层并不等价，
So model, if your neuralnetwork graph is heterogeneous, that it's not like equivalent layers,
那你就需要为不同阶段的不同部分分配不同的设备，对吧？
then you have to align different devices for different parts of the stage, right?
好的。当你完成这个分配后，你会发现对于那个小的蓝色阶段，
Okay. And once you align this you notice that actually for that small stage blue stage,
我们实际上是在四个设备上分配它，那怎么在四个设备上分配一个阶段呢？
we are asking them in four devices and how to ask you a stage in four devices.
这就是你还需要做内部并行的地方，对吧？
That is where you how to also do intraparis, right?
所以基本上在G阶段内部，你会用到多个设备。
So so basically inside of the G stage, you hold multiple devices.
你要做的其实就是，在G阶段内部引入某种形式的内部并行。
And what you do is basically, um, you also introduce some sort of intraparism inside of G stage.
这种方法实际上已经实现了最佳的可扩展性，对吧？
And this method has actually achieved the best scalability, okay?
你要把这种深度神经计算扩展到比如说一千块GPU，基本上就是用这种方式。
The way you skill this deep neuronal computation beyond say 1,000 GPU is basically this.
好的。我认为现在如果你想在一万或两万块GPU上训练神经网络，
Okay. And I think today, if you want to train a neurotro on say, ten k or 20 GPU,
你必须使用这种策略。
you have to use this kind of strategy.
好的，有什么问题吗？
Okay. Any question?
那么总结一下，我们可以通过利用
Okay. So to summarize, okay, um, we can paralyze a single operator by exploiting,
它的内部并行性来并行化单个算子。
uh, its internal partism.
为了做到这一点，对于整个计算图，我们需要为图中的所有节点选择策略，
To do this, for Hu computation graph, we need to choose strategies for all nodes in
以最小化节点成本和边的成本，对吧？
the graph to minimize the node cost and edge cost. Okay?
最后，这个中断和中断
Um, and last, this interrupt and the interrupt
可以结合使用以获得最佳性能，明白吗？
can be combined to achieve the best performance, okay?
在这一部分，
And in this part,
我认为我们主要关注分区。
I think we primarily focus on partism.
但实际上，你所做的基本上也是，你还想把这个
But in reality, what you do is basically, you also want to combine this
和我在上一节课讲过的内容结合起来。
with what I covered in my previous lecture.
明白吗？你想要在启用分区的同时，也启用某种内存对抗机制。
Okay? You want to enable this partism while you also enable some sort of memory opposition.
你开启梯度检查点，开启交换机制。
You turn on grading checkpointing, you turn on swapping.
你还要开启量化、剪枝以及一些低秩近似，
You also turn on quantization, specification and some low rank approximation in order to
以便让你的模型适配有限的边缘设备，明白吗？
fit your model into limited lumbo devices, okay?
因为TPU太贵了。
Because TPU is so expensive.
你想要用很多成本来对待你的模型。
You want to treat your model with a lot of its cost.
好的，所以这基本上就是，呃，内部部分的结束。
Okay, so this is basically the end of, uh intra partism.
有什么问题吗？有。好的，嗯哼。
Any question? Yeah. Okay. Uh huh.
两者。当然是两者。
Both. Of course, both.
是的。因为在这个过程中你是在做内部操作。
Yeah. Because inside the mess you are doing intra op.
你有一个“我”，是的，但minic就像你有一个超高带宽一样。
You have a me, yes, but minic is just like you have a super high bandwidth.
你仍然希望最小化你在An之间交流的信息量。
You still want to minimize the lumbar, the volume of the message you communicate between An.
这样说有道理吗？有。这并不意味着你的通信是无限的，没有成本。
Does that make sense? Yeah. You does not mean that you have infinite the communication has no cost.
是的。如果你在设计策略时不小心，你仍然会很小。
Yeah. If you are not careful on designing the strate, you are still going to be small.
好的。那我们继续进入最后一部分，自动部分编辑。
Okay. Okay, then let's move on to the final section, auto part edition.
好的。嗯，我认为Autopart版本的理念和编译器非常非常相似。
Okay. Um, I think the idea of Autopart edition is very very similar to compiler.
所以你知道，计算机科学家总是想要自动化工作流程，对吧？
So, you know, computer scientists they always want to automate on workflow, right?
设计这种类型的，嗯，
Designing this kind of, like, um,
呃，参数现实非常繁琐而且非常困难。
Uh, paras reality is very tedious and very difficult.
你必须像我说的那样枚举，然后计算成本。
You have to enumerate, like I said, and you count cost.
好吗？所以这个想法是，为什么我们不把它们自动化呢？
Okay? So the idea is why don't we actually automate them?
事实上，自动化非常有意义，因为我觉得在过去几年里，
In fact, automation makes lot of sense because I think in basically past few years,
你可以看到人们开发了许多不同的模型。
you can see people develop many different models.
好的。即使是现在，模型也还在不断发展。
Okay. Even today, models are still evolving a little bit.
比如说，你从……
For example, you evolving from
GBR转化为MOE，再转化为类似MLA的东西，对吧？
GBR rmers into MOE into something like MLA, right?
与此同时，你还会有不同类型的分区，比如数据分区。
And meanwhile, you have different sorts of pisms like data.
操作员，零流水线分区。
Operator, zero Pipeline Pism.
取决于你设计的是哪种模型，以及我们要选择哪种分区方式？
And depending on which model you design and which partism we are going to choose?
人们大致设计了一个系统。好的，就这样。
People roughly design a system. Okay, for it.
好的。你可以看到，如果我们继续扩展模型和分区的数量，
Okay. And you can see, if we continue to skill the number of models and pisms,
我们将要设计更多的系统。
we are going to design one more systems.
基本的想法是，为什么我们不复用一些已有的系统，
The idea is basically, why don't we just actually reuse some of the systems,
对吧？这就是编译器的理念。
right? The compiler philosophy.
为什么我们不复用一些组件，这样我们就可以自动化这个过程。
Why don't we reuse some component, so we can automate this process.
好的，明白了。
Okay. Yeah.
这也解决了许多开发者面临的问题，
And also it solves the problem that facing many, many developers, which are
他们并不是并行系统开发者。
not parallel system developers.
也就是说，哪种并行主义才最适合我的模型，对吧？
That is, which one is which podism is the right fit for my model, right?
好的。那么如果你不考虑现有的系统，如果我告诉你有这样一个系统呢？
Okay. So if you forget about exist systems, so what if I tell you that there's such a system am?
给定任意模型和类的配置，
Given arbitrary model and class config,
我会自动找出最合适的并行策略，
I will automatically figure out the best suitable parallel strategy
例如，最大化训练性能。
that maximize the training performance, for example.
基本上我们可以把它写成这样一个开放的方程式，对吧？
And basically we write down into this kind of opening equation, right?
我们想要最大化性能，也就是要找出最优的策略和方案。
We want to maximize the performance, where we want to figure out the best strategy and the strategy
策略可以看作是由多个内部部分组合而成的。
is strategy shoot as a combination of inter inter parts.
好吗？这基本上就是autoparts试图解决的问题，对吧？
Okay? And this is basically the problem that autoparts trying to solve, okay?
那我们该如何解决这个问题呢？
So how can we solve this problem?
在前面的课程内容中，我们基本上已经建立了
In the previous content of the lecture, we have basically established
一些关于如何分析内部和外部成本的数学理解，对吧？
some mathematical understanding of how to analyze the cost of inter and intra, right?
现在，我们要做的基本上就是把成本写成一个方程，然后尝试去求解它。
Now, what we do is basically we write down the cost into one equation and we try to solve it.
好吗？所以请记住，我们的模型是一个通信图，对吧？
Okay? So remember, our model is a comio graph, right?
就像这个MLP一样。
And such as this MLP.
在我们的大多数设置中，我们的集群基本上是由多个节点组成的，每个节点
And our class in most setup is basically a cluster of nodes where each node
都配备了几个GPU。
is installed with a few GPUs.
就像我说的，在GPU内部，你有manik，这样你就有了相当可观的带宽。
And like I said, inside of GPU, you have manik which you have a decent amount of bandwidth.
但是在节点之间，你只有很少的带宽可以通信。
But between nodes, you have just a little bandwidth to communicate.
我们试图找出一种策略，把这个图划分成某种方式，
And we try to figure out a strategy where we put this, we partition the graph in a way that
以最有效的方式运行。明白吗？
run in the most efficient way. Okay.
正如你可以想象的，嗯，
And as you can imagine, um,
我已经讲了很多关于如何划分算子和阶段的可能性。
I already talked about so many possibilities how to partition operators and stages.
显然，搜索空间非常庞大。
And apparently the sur space is huge.
为了让你感受一下搜索空间有多大，嗯，
To give you a sense how large the sur space is, um,
真实模型中的操作数量大约在11万左右，对吧？有很多矩阵乘加操作。
the number of operations in real model is between 110 k, right? A lot of mad mods.
好的。算子类型的数量基本上是2200，如果你想要更详细地建模的话。
Okay. Number of operator types is basically 2,200 and if you want to model them more.
但我已经说过，最重要的操作空间是Mm。
But I already said that the most important operator space is Mm.
好的，还有教室的大小，对吗？
Okay. And the classroom size, right?
你实际上可以建模多达1000个GPS，甚至更多。
You can actually models up to 1,000 GPS or even more.
好的，所以你基本上需要在这个空间上不断迭代。
Okay. So you have to basically iterate on this space.
好的，以前这个领域的研究人员，基本上发展出了三类
Okay. So in the past, researchers in the area, they basically developed three categories of
可以自动化这种过程的方法。
methods that can basically automate this kind of pardon.
第一类是基于搜索的方法。
The first one is search based.
这一类非常容易理解。
This one is very easy to understand.
你只需要不断枚举即可。
You just keep enumerating.
好的，一旦你有了策略，你就在你的教室上运行它，然后你就会得到一个运行时间，对吗？
Okay. And once you have a strategy, you run um on your classroom and you get a run time, right?
一旦你有了运行时间，你基本上会在你认为更有希望的区域周围进行搜索。
And once you have a run time, you basically try to search around those areas where you think are
当你的预算用完后，你就返回最好的那个结果。
more promising and you return the best one after your budget was exhausted.
明白了吗？这确实是最有效的方法之一。
Okay? And that's indeed one of the most effective way.
大多数公司都是这么做的。
That most companies are doing.
他们基本上就是在进行搜索。
They're basically searching.
第二种方式，就像我说的，类似的思路，是基于学习的方法，用于系统的合并学习。
The second way, like I said, similar recipe, learning based, merge learning for systems.
我们基本上把它表述为一个学习问题，并尝试训练一个模型，
And we basically formulate it as a learning problem and we try to train a model
能够预测出最优的策略。
that can predict what's the best strategy.
这种方法比基于搜索的方法稍微好一些，因为在基于搜索的方法中，
And it's slightly better than search base because in search base,
你基本上是在做某种暴力搜索。
you're basically doing some kind of a brute force searching.
但在基于学习的方法中，你要做的是在收集完数据点之后，
But in learning based, what you do is after you collecting of your data points,
你可以训练一个模型。
you are able to train a model.
希望这些数据点中有一些趋势是你的模型可以捕捉到的。
Hopefully, this data points some trends that your model can capture.
因此，它基本上可以帮助你加速搜索过程。
Therefore, it can basically help you accelerate your search.
好的。第三种方法基本上就是开放式搜索。
Okay. And the third method is basically opienhmbs.
对于开放式搜索，本质上和普通搜索类似，但你引入了一些更智能的
For Opiend hin Base, essentially the same as search, but you are introducing some smarter
比如开放式服务器，可以加速你的搜索。
like open ended servers that can accelerate your search.
好的。接下来我要做的是
Okay. What I'm going to do next is I'm going to very
很快地讲一下第二种和第三种方法。
quickly go through the second one and the third one.
好吗？那我们来看第二种。
Okay? So the second one,
我认为最著名的工作之一就是这个，叫做设备放置组织，
I think one of the most famous work is this one, it's called device placement organization,
还是来自Google Brain。
still from Google Brain.
现在这篇论文的第一作者是斯坦福的教职员工。
And the first author now is faculty at Stanford.
如果你有兴趣申请BC，她非常优秀。好的。
If you're interested in applying for BC, she's pretty good. Okay.
在这门课上，基本上大家用基于学习的方法来解决
And um um, in this class, basically, people use learning based methods to solve
这个基本上是离散优化问题。
this basically, uh discrete ogenation.
最具代表性的方法之一其实就是这个RO，
One of the most representative approach is basically this RO,
Clock RL，也叫做设备放置组织。
um, Clock RL also called device placement organization.
左边我们看到的是一个TensorFlow的计算图，
So on the left, we see a tensor flow, continuo graph,
可视化地展示了这个方法，基本目标是设计和分配设备放置。
visualized interparty the approach basically aims to design assign a device placement
针对图中的每个节点。
for each node in the graph.
也就是说，为每个节点分配一个设备颜色，以最大化分布式执行性能。
That is giving each node a device color in order to maximize the distributed execution performance.
在这里，这种方法基本上只在互操作性的空间中起作用，
And here, the approach basically works only on the space of interoperatism,
正如你可以想象的，因为它实际上只为每个节点分配一种颜色。
as you can imagine, because it actually only assigns one color for each node.
这就是为什么它只能捕捉到中断与不中断的可能性。
That's why it only captures the possibility in interrupt not interrupt.
在这个空间下，基本上是用一个机器模型来
And given this space, it's basically use a machinery model to
预测图中每个节点的放置位置。
predict the placement of each node in the graph.
有时候，尤其是在训练的早期阶段，机器模型可能会出错。
Well, sometimes, especially in the early phase of training, the machinary model can go wrong.
我基本上是在真实集群上评估这个预测，以获得它的真实运行时间，也就是性能。
I basically evaluated this prediction on real cluster to get its real runtime. Uh, performance.
然后我需要把真实的随机数据反馈给预测模型，并且
I need to then fits the real random data back to the predictive model and
使用策略梯度来更新其性能。
update its performance using policy gradients.
所以策略梯度基本上就是我们现在用来训练强化学习模型的方法。
So policy gradient is basically the one we use to train reimburse learning models today.
PPO、DPO、GRPO，它们都是策略梯度方法。
And um PPO, DPO GRPO, they are all policy gradients.
好的。我需要重复这个策略梯度更新过程，直到找到一个足够好的模型。
Okay. I need to repeat this policy gradient update process until a good enough model is fun.
足够好的策略就可以了。
Good enough strategy is fine.
好的，就像这样。
Okay? Like this.
好的，在这些圆圈中，机械模型基本上被具体化为
Okay. And in the circles the machinery model is basically materialized as
一个简单的循环神经网络，如这张幻灯片所示。
a simple recurrent neural network shown on this slide.
好的，这个部分的工作原理如下。
Okay. This arm basically works as follows.
首先，它将控制图线性化为一个节点序列。
So it first, nearize the cotero graph as a sequence of nodes.
And then each node corresponds to one operator.
That is nariz entire graph as a sequence, like a sentence, sting language model.
Okay. And I give you a name, for example, op one up to op 100, blah, blah, blah.
Okay. And then it will embed each node as a feature actor embedding.
So it's a typical recipe of train language models, but it's for training commit graph.
Okay. And then you basically once you get the embedding, you are able to fit this into a sequence
to sequence prediction model, right?
You basically predict the placement of each node. That's it.
Okay. Very simple.
Another objective is a typical reinforced learning objective, where you try to maximize
你的位置条件下的期望奖励。
the expected reward conditional on your placement.
这个目标可以通过策略成分进行优化。
And this objective can be optimized using policy ingredient.
好的，那它的表现如何呢？
Okay, so how does this perform?
根据论文，它确实返回了一些
According to the paper, um, it indeed return some placement strategies that are
比专家设计的最佳方案还要好20%到30%的布局策略。
20 to 30% better than the best available ones designed by experts.
如果你看看可视化结果，就是用这种方法为
And if you take a look, um, at the visualization, which is a strategy found by this method for
谷歌著名的Inception WT模型找到的策略，我会说
the very famous inception WT model by Google, um, I would say
这绝对不是人类能想到的东西。
it's certainly something that cannot be found by human.
好吗？我觉得人类很难直观地设计出这种布局，
Okay? I don't think a human is very intuitive to design this kind of like a placement,
对吧？是的，这很奇怪。
right? Yeah, it's weird.
但就像我说的，这种方法的资源利用率并不高，因为它需要用整个集群
But like I said, this method is not very resource efficient because it has to use the entire cluster
来对某一个给定的部署策略进行真实评估。
to perform a real evaluation for one given placement strategy.
这会消耗大量资源。
That takes a lot of resources.
而且你们可能已经知道，
And as you probably already know,
O 的效率也不是很高。
O is not very efficient as well.
是的，这不是一种很高效的学习策略，所以需要很多次迭代。
Yeah, it's not a very efficient learning strategy, so it takes a lot of iterations.
这也是为什么这种方法只在 Google 内部使用。
That's why this method is only populated inside of Google.
我觉得在 Google 之外，没人用这种方法。
I think outside of Google, nobody uses this one.
我们接下来讲第二种课堂方法，基本上是最优实例化方法。
Let's move on to second classroom method, basically optimal inst based method.
因为这个离散策略空间极其复杂。
So um, since this discrete strategy space is extremely complex.
所以这种基于选项的方法的基本原理其实是，嗯，
So the rationale behind this option based method is basically, um,
我们尝试利用分割策略的一些结构来减少
we try to leverage some structures of the parting strategy to reduce
空间，直到问题规模变得可以用现有的操作器解决，明白吗？
the space until the problem size is, um, doable, using existing opiors, okay?
比如说，IOP服务器，或者像DP这样的东西，明白吗？
For example, IOP server or like DP over, this kind of thing, okay?
希望这种空间缩减的启发式方法不会损失最优性，
And the hope is that this space reduction, um, uh, heuristic does not actually lose any optimality,
有时候确实是这样的，明白吗？
which sometimes could be true, okay?
嗯，让我来介绍一下这个方法，这也是我的论文。
Um, let me introduce this method and this is my paper.
好的，我觉得这是一篇不错的论文。
Okay. And I think this is a good paper.
是的，我用这篇论文拿到了南加大的教职。
Yeah, I use this paper to get a faculty at USD. Yeah.
好的，嗯，首先，回忆一下在本部分一开始，我们是怎么解释很多内容的
Okay. Um, to begin, um, recall that at the beginning of this part, right, how we explained a lot in
互操作和互操作部分及其独特特性。
interop and interop parts and their unique characteristics.
所以基本上，互操作通信，呃，通信较少，但有设备ID，对吧？
So basically, basically interop communication, uh communicate less, but has device id, right?
气泡。但实际上互操作通信更多，嗯，但它有更高的统一性。
Bubble. But the interop actually communicate more, um, but it has a higher unition.
好的。那么给定一个社区图和一个集群，我们如何找到一个好的策略
Okay. So given a communal graph and a cluster, so how can we find the good strategy
从互操作和互操作分区的组合空间中？这就是我们的问题。
from the combined space of Inter and interop partism? That's our problem.
所以我们基本上设计了一个叫Opa的算法。
So we basically design this algorithm called Opa.
这个Opa算法基本上利用了如今许多集群具有对应结构的事实。
And this Opa basically leverage the fact that many today cluster has a corresponding structure.
即紧密分布在一个节点上的设备，它们可以通过Minik通信
That is closely located devices in one node, they can communicate with Minik
也就是高带宽，对吧？
which is high bandwidth, right?
而分布在不同节点的远程设备，它们可以通过……
And distant devices across different nodes, they can communicate with they
只能以低带宽进行通信。
can only communicate with low bandwidth.
好吗？鉴于这种，嗯，嗯，鉴于这种特性
Okay? And given this kind of like, um, um, given this kind of characteristics
你基本上可以找到一种对齐方式，就是在互操作性上层的那部分，
and you can basically find alignment that is, in the upper part of the interperism,
他们基本上倾向于，呃，他们倾向于选择带宽不是很高的通信方式，
they basically favor, uh they favor some communication bandwidths that is not so high,
因为它们通信量很少。
because it communicate pretty less.
所以你基本上可以在节点之间映射这种互操作性。
So basically you can map this interopism across nodes.
你让大部分的并行发生在不同节点之间的TPU之间分布。
You let most of the parism happening between TPUs distribute across different nodes.
但对于互操作性，就像我说的，他们需要大量带宽来
But for interperism, like I said, they need a lot of bandwis to
通信以提高效率。
communicate in order to be efficient.
所以你必须把这种互操作性映射到分组中。
So you have to map this kind of inter parism into veining.
所以你只允许这些通信发生在aminis中。
So you only allow those communication happening into aminis.
这基本上就给你带来了这样的对齐方式。
And this basically give you alignment like this.
那你觉得如果让所有的交互都发生在链路之间，这样工作怎么样？
So how about you just part in working in a way that all the inter parism happening across link.
但所有的交互基本上都是在不同节点之间发生的。
But all the interparism basically happen across different nodes.
这是一个很强的启发式方法，因为你现在不需要在所有空间中搜索了。
This is a strong heuristics because now you don't have to search over all the spaces.
你只需要为每个子问题进行搜索。
You just need to search for each subproblem.
这样说有道理吗？
Does this into make sense?
好的，酷，这也许可行。
Okay. Cool. Yeah, this may work.
是的，我希望这样说清楚了。
Yeah, I hope that makes sense.
好的，嗯，这个原理帮助Opa基本上解耦并重新组织了搜索空间。
Okay um the rationale helps Opa to basically decouple and reorganize the search space.
基本上，这个Opa实现了完整的模型并行。
Basically, this Opa generates a full model parallel.
通过分层指定互操作和并行策略来进行策略选择。
Asking strategy by hierarchically specifying interop
并且在每一层分别指定互操作和并行策略。
and inter parallel strategy respectively at each level.
更具体地说，这个Opa基本上会在第一层搜索互操作并行方案，
More specifically, this Opa will basically, uh search for inter parallel plan at
也就是如何把计算图切分成不同的阶段。
the first level that is how to cut the graph into different stages.
然后在下一层，Opa会为每个互操作并行阶段推导出最佳的并行方案。
And then at the next level, uh, upper derives the best interop parallel plan
对于互操作并行方案的每个阶段，都会推导出最佳的并行方案。
for each stage of the interop parallel plan.
通过设计一种算法，使得每个子问题在局部上都是最优的。
And by designing an algorithm that are basically both locally optimal for each subproblem.
但我们并不保证全局最优。
But we don't guarantee global optimality.
我们只是设计了一些算法，能够保证在第一层是最优的。
We are just designing algorithms that can guarantee like we are optimal at the first level
并且在第二层是最优的，我们希望得到的策略足够好，
and optimal at the second level, and we hope the yielded strategy is good enough,
因为我们已经利用了理论映射来连接不同的并行方式。好的。
because we already leverage the uretical mapping the binaries between parisms. Okay.
这是一个很棒的想法。好的。这一页是
That's a Halla idea. Okay. And this slide is
基本上给出了优化过程的一个概览，好吗？
basically give an overview of ogenation processes, okay?
输入是计算图和计算机集群。
The inputs, computational graph and computer cluster.
这个OPA会经过两轮处理来完成这个优化。
And this OPA goes through two passes to do this openation.
所以第一轮中断处理，主要是找到最佳的中断部分策略
So the first interrupt pass, it basically finds the best interrupt part strategy
使用动态规划算法，这个我稍后会解释。
with the dynamic programming algorithm, which I explain later.
然后第二轮中断路径会用整数规划方法
And then the second interrup path will find the best inter parallel strategy
找到最佳的跨并行策略。
with integer a programming organization.
好吗？这个优化是分层的，这意味着更高层级的中断路径会导致
Okay? And this optim is hierarchical, which means that the higher level interrupt paths will cause
更低层级的中断路径多次做出决策，这些决策是基于反馈格式的。
lower level interruple paths multiple times to make a decision based on feedback format.
也就是说，在两个层级上进行优化，明白吗？
That is optimize at two levels, okay?
我会尝试以某种方式将结果结合起来。
And I try to combine the results in some way.
好的。那么你是怎么做到的呢？
Okay. So how do you do this?
那我们通过一个例子来演示一下op引擎是如何工作的。
So let's walk through an example and show how the op engine works.
好吗？对于中断传递，基本上，给定这样一个可交换图，
Okay? So for the interrupt pass, um, so basically, given this commuting graph,
我们需要把图切分成多个阶段，以形成流水线。
right, we need to cut graph into multiple stages to form a pipeline.
这就是中断。而且对这个图有不同的分页方式，
That's interrupt. And there are different ways of paging this graph,
在这个中断策略空间里。
um, in this interrupt strategy space.
所以我们想要得到最优的方案，对吧？
So we want to get the best one. Okay?
我只解决子问题，
I only solve for the subroglem,
目前我不担心如何在这个阶段内部解决它。
I don't worry at this moment how to solve it inside of this stage.
好的，所以即使我们选择了一种划分图的方法，比如像这个选择，假设
Okay. So even if we pick a way to part a graph, such as this one choose, suppose
我们选择了这个，这个是最优的。
we pick this one, this one is optimal.
我们仍然需要为每个阶段分配一组设备，来让阶段使用内部划分。
We still need to assign each stage to a set of devices to ask the stage using intrap parti.
这是问题的第二层。
That's the second level of the problem.
所以为了做到这一点，基本上我们把所有设备抽象成二维的。
So in order to do so, basically we abstract out all the devices as two D.
设备网格，像这样，四乘四。
Device mash like this, four by four.
并且假设每个网格维度上的设备具有相同的通信带宽。
Okay. And assume that the device along each match dimension has the same communicating bandwidth.
比如说，对于像这样的TPGPU教室，我们可以把一个维度设置为所有节点。
For example, for TPGPU classroom like this, we can set one dimension to
节点，好的。
be all the nodes, nodes, okay.
并且所有沿着这个维度的通信都会经过，
And all the communication along this dimension will go through,
就像我说的，慢速的跨节点互连，对吧？
like I said, slow cross node interconnects, right?
我们可以把另一个维度设置为所有GPU，而不是节点。
We can set another dimension to be all the GPs instead of node.
所以沿着这个维度通信会非常快，通过Milink。
So communicating along this dimension is pretty fast. Go through Milink.
好的。所以我们的做法基本上是为每个阶段分配设备，呃，呃，通过从这个设备教室中选择
Okay. So what we do is basically we assign devices, um, um, uh, to each stage by pick
最佳的子匹配方案。
the best submatch choice from this device classroom.
所以我们会不断枚举。
So we keep enumerating.
好的，我们把设备划分成子组，然后把它分配给上层的分区，我们
Okay, we partition the device into subgroups and we assign that to the upper partitioning and we
评估并找出运行时间。
evaluate and find out the runtime.
然后我们会不断尝试，直到找到最优的方案。好的。
And then we keep trying until we figure out the one that is the best. Okay.
嗯，所以基本上我们发现这个联合问题，就是如何划分
Um, so basically we basically find that this joint problem of how to partition
计算图，以及如何为每个阶段分配
the computi graph and how to assign each assign how to assign each parton stage to
设备网格中的一组设备。
a set of device from the device mesh.
它们可以很好地被表述为一个动态规划程序，基本目标是最小化
They can be nicely formulated as a dynamic programming program, which basically minimize
流水线的执行时间，对吧？
the pipeline execution time, okay?
但是，为了解决这个动态规划问题，我们还需要知道
Um, but in order to solve this dynamic programming, uh, we also need to know the optimal time
在对齐的网格上运行一个阶段的最优时间。
of running a stage on align mesh.
因为，如果你为这个设备选择了动态网格，如果你为这个阶段的这一部分选择了这个子网格，
Because S, if you pick dynamesh for this device, if you pick this submash for this part of stage,
你仍然需要知道在这个平台上运行那个图的最佳方式是什么，
you still need to know what is the best way of running that graph on this mash,
使用你最好的内部并行方式。
using your best introp partism.
所以你还会遇到另一个你可能想要解决的层级选项，就是关于内部并行的。
So you are subject to another level option you probably want to solve, which is for the intrap.
好吗？嗯，我今天大概就这些内容了。
Okay? Yeah, I think that is all I have today.
我打算下次，也许周四完成这个，然后我们再转到Mo。好的，谢谢。
I'm going to finish this next maybe on Thursday and then we move onto Mo. Cool. Thank you.